<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 01:24:18 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 01:24:18 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 044, Sugar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A carbohydrate used to address your loved one because of its sweetness. But sugar is not good for your body, not your loved ones — or maybe but the carbohydrate. Sugar is bitter to you and your body. It has a drug like effect at the center of the brain. Sweet food — just like salty and fatty food — can produce addiction-like effects in the human brain. It makes you lose self-control, drives your anxiety and oftentimes triggers your overeating habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early humans when the food was scarce, sugar acted like a high-calorie food. But now when the food is abundant, it contributes to obesity and diabetes. Overeating alters the brain reward system which in turn drives overeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glucose, Fructose, Sucrose, Maltose, Lactose, Dextrose, Starch are all types of sugar. Check the labels on your food items. Sugar isn’t just in candies and dessert, it’s also added to tomato sauce, yogurt, flavoured water etc. Since sugar is everywhere it’s important to understand how it affects the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever Since it is found everywhere, chances are you are overdoing it. In excess, it negatively affects your body and brain. Eating sugar rewards your brain — dopamine release reward. Whole food doesn’t release as much dopamine as sugar does. Dopamine gives you the feeling of pleasure. Once you get used to it, dopamine regulates your moods. As soon as you eat sugar your blood pressure rises and gives you a quick burst of energy. But as it starts to break and get absorbed in the body you start to get jittery and anxious. In turn, you eat more sugar and this makes the situation worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive sugar causes tooth decay, causes inflammation on the skin and makes skin age faster. The extra insulin in your bloodstream can make walls of arteries grow thicker which in turn gets stiffer, stressing the heart. This passive damage causes heart diseases like heart attack, stroke, heart failure etc. Similarly, Pancreas get overworked while pumping out more and more insulin. Too much sugar can lead to kidney failure. One who consumes more sugar weighs more and we are aware of the downsides of obesity. Each of these exploits your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, think about all the different kinds of sugar. Each one is unique but each one causes a dopamine trigger making it more addictive. In this way, excessive sugar acts like a drug.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 043, Cannabis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Marijuana, Weed, 420, Ganjha, Kush, Pot, Hemp — whatever you want to call it. There are millions of names for Cannabis and there are millions of people who smoke it everyday. Weed has been an integral part of religion and society of India. For a long time Indians used cannabis freely. Its use is also mentioned in Atharvaveda and Ayurveda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A verse from Atharvaveda. Book 11, Hymn 8 (or 6), Verse 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;पञ्च राज्यानि वीरुधां सोमश्रेष्ठानि ब्रूमः। दर्भो भङ्गो यवः सह ते नो मुञ्चन्त्व् अंहसः॥&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To the five kingdoms of the plants which Soma rules as Lord we speak.
Darbha, hemp, barley, mighty power: may these deliver us from woe. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/cannabis-one-sacred-plant-atharva-veda-sindhu-karpakal&quot;&gt;[Source]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayurveda suggests that the medicinal benefits of marijuana can be used as the treatment against psychosis, anxiety, depression. Also, it suggests, taking excessive amounts of marijuana can dry up the body and hence create imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atharvaveda suggests it brings joy. Lord Shiva is often found with a chillum. Most sadhus and pir baba communicate with God via communal smoking session. Bhang thandai is mandatory on Holi and Maha Shivratri as it is the holy offering. For those of you who don’t know, Bhang is a strain of Cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delhi alone consumes 38,260 kg of cannabis every year, making it the third largest consumer in the world, after New York and Karachi. Mumbai ranks sixth with a consumption of 32,400 kg weed. If the government legalises it, cannabis has a wide market and will add a part to GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a stigma around weed in our country. This exists because any substance that affects your brain is considered bad, unhealthy, unprofessional. I am not saying we should legalise it right away but to break the chain and leave it open for a healthy discussion. Marijuana became illegal in India in 1985, under the Narcotics and Psychotropic Act. It was because of two reasons 1) Because of India’s commitment to the International Treaty on Narcotics. 2) Pressure by the United States because of their participation in the “war on drugs”. Instead of regulating its supply, like an economic commodity, the government simply cut it. Slowly it became a taboo to even talk about it. In recent years, legalizing weed for medicinal use has caught lots of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people suggest weed causes psychotic effects — which is not entirely correct. Weed has two major compounds TetraHydroCannabinol (THC) which gives the feeling of ‘high’. And CBD or Cannabidiol which is non-psychoactive. This means CBD can cancel out the psychotic effects of THC. In recent times, recreational weed has a high amount of THC and less levels of CBD, which gives you a good ‘high’. But because of this, people who are dealing with depression or anxiety or Post Traumatic Stress Disorder can have severe panic attacks. That’s why you need a good amount of CBD in your weed. CBD also helps in chronic pain and can help in recovery of cancer patients, treat depression, help people with epilepsy and Attention Deficit Disorder as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is said weed is a ‘gateway drug’. But it is not entirely supported by Science. Instead 9% of the people get addicted to weed compared to 32% and 15% of alcohol and tobacco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being illegal, the peddlers add toxic substances to it. This might actually end up screwing lots of people. And if it’s legalized, the government can actually maintain standards which will not adversely affect the health of people. Government can connect the dots between legalization, commercialization and decriminalization. I think legalizing weed might just do a lot more good than harm. Yes, I am thinking all wrong! Oh, stupid student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you think it should be legalized or not?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cannabis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cannabis/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 042, March Past</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;August 15, Independence day was approaching. Preparation for the national festival was all over the school, I was in class 4. A shy, small, lean but mischievous kid. Annoying the bullies and meddling with them was my favorite pastime. Sneaking through the class as soon as the recess bell rang. Skipping stairs, running in corridors, poking people with rubber, making up stories was a part of school chores. Obviously, studying was the least favorite thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before Independence Day, students, teachers, non-teaching staff everyone was busy with different errands — reciting national anthem, practising cultural dance, coordinating for march past etc. Quizzes, debates, drawing and many more competitions were organized. Just like me, no one wanted to attend classes. I tried my hands on a general knowledge quiz but answered several questions wrong, verdict — not selected. Then the choir, I mispronounced a word in the stanza, I was kicked. Debating and dancing never interested me. Only option left was participating in the parade. It was closest related to the ground activity, perhaps sports. And definitely better than sitting in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 8 classes of 40 minutes each, we spent the last 6 classes on ground practising the march past, perfecting the leg moment, arm rotation, keeping the head straight, saluting the flag but mostly fun. We traveled with a ball in a bag. We used to run or play with the ball or hide and seek or just roaming the theater hall or intruding on the stage preparation. Often we were scolded for being late. But modern problems require modern solutions. We used to keep a water bottle with us all the time and whenever our teacher asked us where we were, the water bottle rescued us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next was the teacher’s move. They found a solution to deal with the problem. What’s better than a competition between units. There were five units to depict the colors of the flag — Saffron, white, blue for chakra then white and then green. Believe me, teachers are pure genius. They followed the infamous ‘divide and rule’ policy to add aesthetics to the parade. They suggested whichever unit will look coordinated and more disciplined will get an award. It was the misuse of our innocence. Our head boy led the parade with a flagpole in hands and sharpness in his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rehearsals were done. It was August 14, we were all distributed with colored wrist bands to make up for the depicted flag color. Finally, the day had come, Independence Day. We were in school enjoying the patriotic songs on speakers. The ceremony started with our parade. All the marchers were dressed in white colored uniforms and an allocated wrist band. The troops were giving their best to win. But in that smear moment as I glanced through the parade it looked beautiful. A perfect symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marchers sat down as the ceremony progressed. Patriot dance, skits, speeches everything was amazing. But we, marchers, were waiting for the award ceremony. We were waiting to know whose battalion was the best. Award after award, the ceremony ended. In that utter moment, we felt as if we were cheated. The hard work did not go in vain. We had a lot of fun and the laddoos.
Period&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/March-Past/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/March-Past/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 041, Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mathematics-of-generative-adversarial-network&quot;&gt;Mathematics of Generative Adversarial Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/GAN1/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the basics of GANs. In today’s post we will delve right into the mathematics of the GAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the zero sum non cooperative game. If one wins then the other loses. This zero-sum game is also known as a minimax game. Discriminator (\(D\)) is trained to maximize the probability of assigning the correct label to both training examples and samples from Generator (\(G\)). While the generator maximizes probability of (\(D\)) to make mistakes, by minimizing the log of the inverse probability predicted by the discriminator for fake images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GAN.gif&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generator’s distribution \((p_g)\) over \(x\) is defined on prior input noise variable \(p_z(z)\). A neural network framework \(G\) is defined to learn data distribution \(x\). \(G\) maps noise variable to data space as \(G(z; \theta_g)\).&lt;br /&gt;
\(D(x;\theta_d\) outputs a scalar. \(D(x)\) represents probability that \(x\) comes from data whereas in \(D(G(z))\) the \(G(z)\) is from generator network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(G\) is trained to minimize \(\log(1-D(G(z)))\). \(D\) and \(G\) plays minimax game with the value function \(V(G,D)\):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\min_{G}\max_{D}V(D,G) = E_{x\sim p_{data}(x)}[\log(D(x))]\;+\;E_{z\sim p_{z}(z)}[\log(D(G(z)))]\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;~ means &quot;has distribution (of)&quot;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adversarial training principle has transformed unsupervised task to supervised task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optimality&quot;&gt;Optimality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle of GANs is based on Nash Equilibrium. This means, theoretically, the algorithm tries to achieve global optimality \(p_g\;=\;p_{data}\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preposition :&lt;/strong&gt; For \(G\) fixed, the optimal discriminator is &lt;br /&gt;
\[D_{G}^{\ast}(x) = \frac{p_{data}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\]
&lt;em&gt;Proof :&lt;/em&gt; To train \(D\) we maximize the value function, keeping \(G\) fixed.&lt;br /&gt;
\[V(G,D) = \int_{x}\;p_{data}(x)\log(D(x))dx\;+\int_{z}p_z(z)\log(1-D(g(z)))dz \]
\[= \int_{x}\;p_{data}(x)\log(D(x))dx\;+\;p_g(x)\log(1-D(x)))dx \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any \(a,b \in R^2\) such that \(a,b \neq {0,0} \). Then the function \(f \; \rightarrow a\log(y) + b\log(1-y)\) achieves maxima at \(\frac{a}{a\;+\;b}\).&lt;br /&gt;
Discriminator is defined within \(supp(p_{data}) \cup supp(p_g)\)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Definition: \(supp(x)\) is the subset of the domain containing those elements that are not mapped to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training objective of discriminator can be reframed as maximum log-likelihood for estimating conditional probability \(P(Y=y\;\vert \;x)\). Thus the minmax equation can be reformulated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[C(G)\; =\; \max_D V(G,D)\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\;+\;E_{z\sim p_{z}}[\log(D_G^\ast(G(z)))]\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\;+\;E_{x\sim p_{g}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}\left[\log\left(\frac{p_{data}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\right)\right]\;+\;E_{x\sim p_{g}}\left[\log\left(\frac{p_{g}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\right)\right]\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of Course the aim of GAN is \(p_g\;=\;p_{data}\).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 040, Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we will be talking about Generative Adversarial Network because they are cool and they can do lots of cool things. People use to create sketches, write poems, edit videos. The infamous DeepFakes uses GAN. It is an approach to generative modeling using deep learning methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduced in 2014, by Ian Goodfellow, the objective of the GAN is to create fake images that are as realistic as possible. GAN is based on a game theory objective to find &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nash_equilibrium&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt; between Generator and Discriminator, two components of GAN. The two networks, Generator and Discriminator, play a zero-sum game against each other until the discriminator is fooled for at least half the number of times. The generator converts random noise into observations that look as if they have been sampled from the original dataset while the discriminator tries to distinguish between the real and fake samples. The key to GAN lies in how we alternate the training between the networks so that the generator learns to fool the discriminator, while the discriminator gets better at correctly identifying fake samples. This drives the generator to fool the discriminator in more engaging ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Generator Model&lt;/strong&gt;
The generator model takes a fixed size random vector and generates samples in the domain. The vector is randomly sampled from Gaussian Distribution, which seeds the generative process. The aim of the generator is to learn the data distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Discriminator Model&lt;/strong&gt;
The discriminator model takes an example from the domain (real or generated) and predicts the binary class of the sample (real or fake). The real examples come from training data while the fake examples are created by a generator network. The discriminator is a simple classification model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the training process, the generator model is kept and used to generate new samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GANs have the power to generate data similar to the training data. Thus they help in data augmentation. GANs provide a more domain-specific approach for data augmentation. Besides this, GANs have many other applications — Image superresolution, Creating Art, Image-to-Image translation, Drug Designing etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most compelling reason why GANs are used is because of their success. Since 2014 when GAN was first introduced, the results through the model are getting better manifolds every year. GANs have been able to generate samples so realistic that humans are unable to tell the difference between fake and real.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN1/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 039, Sponge City</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The entire world is filled with concrete. Natural water system is disregarded. In the meantime,  extreme weather conditions — floods, droughts — are frequent because of climate change. China has been hard hit by this. To solve this problem, they came up with the idea of Sponge City in 2015. No no, it isn’t the place where Spongebob Squarepants lives. Instead, it is a city structured to absorb and capture rainwater. It helps in flood prevention. It is a sustainable, regenerative, eco-friendly, low-impact, future-proofed, zero-carbon solution for the drainage system at urban scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before explaining more about what Sponge City actually is, let us first understand what issues does Sponge City intends to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water Scarcity in urban and semi-urban areas —&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the time we get water from aquifers underneath us. The rainwater is absorbed by the ground and is filtered through. This water reflourishes the aquifers. With extreme urbanization and impermeable concrete structures, the aquifers cannot restore to their levels. Thus less water is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polluted water discharged into the rivers and seas —&lt;/strong&gt; Now that water cannot be absorbed, it gets drained into sewage. This mixture is more polluted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Degradation of urban ecosystem and increase in the intensity of flooding —&lt;/strong&gt; Because of urbanization and industrialization there is a drastic change in the climatic conditions. This leads to extreme weather conditions. Flooding leads to water clogging and disturbances in the natural water cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deal with these problems, the idea of Sponge City has surfaced. The idea of Sponge City is to create a pervious system to allow the flow of water. The water is absorbed in the sponge-like environment and is stored in urban aquifers which can be used by the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sponge city needs to be abundant with space that allows water to seep through it. Besides the permeable asphalt and water-absorbing materials, a sponge city requires contiguous open green spaces, interconnected channels and ponds that can naturally store and filter water. Green roofs can retain and filter water before releasing it into ground. More importantly, moderating the usage of water is very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sponge city provides a wide range of advantages. More clean water, Cleaner groundwater, reduction in flood risks, greener and healthier environment. Inspired by this model, lately, many countries are studying and trying to incorporate this system into their environment.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sponge-City/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sponge-City/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 038, Minimalism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What comes into your mind when you think of minimalism? A perfectly lit white room with no material or extremely simple artwork. That’s how the concept of minimalism is portrayed. But when it comes to living a minimalist life, living in a well lighted room without any material would be quite morbid and deprecating. Some people follow this extreme form of minimalism; it’s not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism is not about removing everything but it’s about decluttering in order to achieve happiness, peace and sanctity. Consider an example: A person wants a cup of coffee after waking up to feel alive or happy. They start to think this is what makes them happy. But slowly this requirement locks them in. They start to structure their life around it. For a lot of us, it’s evening tea or the Internet for entertainment and news or the need to watch TV in the evening to unwind time. There is nothing wrong with it. But gradually these things which make us happy start to pile up and control our life. What happens if you let go of these things and keep it as a “nice-to-have” option? It might make you feel sad for a while but it will free you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism is intentionally living with things you really need — those items that support the purpose. Removing all the distractions of excess possessions to focus more on things that matter. Living a minimalist lifestyle reduces your stress and anxiety, improves your sleep, helps in clarity of thoughts, boosts your productivity and creativity and importantly helps you to save money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you start to declutter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are new, start with 5 minutes a day to build momentum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put everything in one pile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask yourself: do you really need this? Do you use it regularly? Do you love it? If the answer to any of these is no, then recycle, donate, or give it to someone who might want it. Put it in a box for these purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to do more than 5 minutes a day, go ahead but be careful not to overdo it in the beginning or you will think it’s difficult to continue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical decluttering is just one type, you should declutter your digital life as well. Declutter your calendar by prioritizing your commitments and saying no to non-essential things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a beautiful world of freedom and fresh breath hiding behind that clutter. Deciding how to declutter your home is up to you. A minimalist lifestyle teaches you how to say “No” to unsolicited things. This isn’t a prescription for how to live your life, but just something to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Minimalism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Minimalism/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 037, PS5</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Decepticons! The new flagship of Playstation is there. With high collar esque, Sony has unveiled PS5 — a console from an alien world.  Through the innumerous rumours, it’s been 7 years since PS4 was launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sony, on June 11, 2020, during the Sony PS5 reveal event showed off lots of games including Gran Turismo, Spider-Man : Miles Morales, Horizon 2: Forbidden West and many more. But the showstopper was the revelation  of the PS5 console itself. Sony uncovered two variants of PS5 which will be available at launch — PS5 and PS5 Digital Edition. The only difference between the two is that PS5 Digital Edition does not have Blu-ray drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS5 features a custom eight-core AMD Zen 2 CPU clocked at 3.5 GHz and a custom GPU  based on AMD’s RDNA 2 architecture hardware which promises 10.28 teraflops and 36 compute units clocked at 2.23GHz. To further improve the performance, Sony has replaced the HDD with an 825GB SSD and the 8 GB of DDR3 RAM of PS4 with 16 GB of GDDR6 RAM in PS5. The new PS5 provides a stunning gaming experience. Benchmarking Ray Tracing and super fast refresh rate of 120 Hz - the new iconic PS5 gives the user an exhilarating gaming experience. With an 8K Output support, Sony has truly created a futuristic machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sony, alongside PS5, introduced the DualSense game controller. It provides haptic feedback and adaptive triggers for an immersive gaming experience. The angle of hand trigger is also tweaked and the grip is provided to suffice ergonomics. The controller has an array of in-built microphone for in-game chat. To create epic gameplay, Sony has upgraded their Share button to Create button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As good as it may sound, PS5’s rival Xbox Series X is equally futuristic. With a custom processor of 12 teraflops, hardware accelerated ray tracing, variable rate shading Xbox might have a slight margin over PS5. Xbox has a black industrial design and vents on top with an underlying green sheet giving it a green halo which makes it look minimal yet modern. Compared to Xbox’s design, the rectangular design of PS5 has curves instead of edges. But PS5 has a very controversial design, the white plastic doesn’t have good respect in the techworld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bummer that they both did not reveal its price and release date but we can expect them in Holiday season 2020. I cannot wait to try them out. Oh poor boy! I cannot afford it. If you feel like gifting it, I won’t mind.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/PS5/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/PS5/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 036, Phi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh No! Not another greek alphabet. Do I have an obsession with them? Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/Pi/&quot;&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;, Phi is a symbolic representation of Golden Ratio. Golden Ratio, what? I have never heard of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find the &lt;strong&gt;Golden Ratio&lt;/strong&gt; when we divide the a line into two parts such that the ratio of the longer part to the shorter part is equal to the whole length divided by the shorter part.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GoldenRatio.png&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{a}{b} = \frac{a+b}{a}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic begins,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{a}{b} = 1 + \frac{a}{b}\]
\[\varphi = 1 + \frac{1}{\varphi}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention anything about recursion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = 1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{\ddots}}}}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevermind, let’s calculate its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(\varphi \)  is a solution of quadratic equation \(\varphi^2 - \varphi - 1 = 0\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{1+\sqrt{5}}{2} = 1.6180339887…\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another irrational number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the 1D line we can extend this in 2D. A 2D rectangle with side length \(a + b\) and \(a\). Following the properties of Golden Ratio, this rectangle is known as &lt;strong&gt;Golden Rectangle&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/goldenREc.png&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more to it. What if we subdivide the rectangle into a square and another rectangle and do it until we get two squares? Adding to it if we construct a spiral by pivoting at the corner of the square and turning it quarter in a continuous fashion, we will get &lt;strong&gt;Golden Spiral&lt;/strong&gt;. It is an ever-expanding spiral.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/spiralGolden.jpg&quot; height=&quot;40%&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s look from a different direction — bottom up. Consider two unit squares, combine them along the side. Attach a square of side length equal to the length of the larger side of the previously formed rectangle. We will get a similar pattern again. But if we look at the side length of squares we will find an engaging pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Length of the side of the next square is equal to the sum of the previous two. Remember &lt;strong&gt;Fibonacci Series&lt;/strong&gt;. When we take the ratio of two successive numbers from the Fibonacci Sequence then their value is very close to Golden Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B/A&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6667&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.625&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.615&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach towards infinity this ratio converges to the Golden Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough of mathematics Square. We understand, Golden Ratio has myriads of secrets. Why should we care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This divine proportion is all around us but its knowledge is confined to some mainstream recognition. Just like air — it’s there but we can’t see it. Similarly, Golden Ratio is omnipresent — from nature to music to architectural design. This tool is used by sculptors and artists to achieve remarkably accurate proportion and aesthetic compositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, we can find many instances of phi. The first guy was Luca Pacioli, a Franciscan friar who wrote a book called &lt;em&gt;De Divina Proportione&lt;/em&gt; back in 1509, which was named after the golden ratio. He did not tell about the aesthetics of Phi, instead the book focused on the Vitruvian System and its allegiance with golden ratio. Leonardo da Vinci was close friends with Pacioli. Da Vinci used this secret math in many of his famous paintings including Monalisa. Ancient Greek architecture used the Golden Ratio to determine pleasing dimensional relationships between the width of a building and its height, the size of the portico and even the position of the columns supporting the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phi is also said to be common in nature. Flower petals often come in Fibonacci numbers, such as five or eight, and pine cones grow their seeds outward in spirals of Fibonacci numbers. The ubiquitous nature of the Golden Ratio with its diverse and engaging application have made Phi another mathematical marvel.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Phi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Phi/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 035, Understanding Deep Learning Requires Rethinking Generalization</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a summary of Understanding Deep Learning Requires Rethinking Generalization paper which has been awarded for the best paper award at ICLR 2017. One of the best papers I have read so far, an eye-opener but quite verbose.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some models generalize better than others. But how do we distinguish between them? Answering this question would help us interpret the Artificial Neural Network (ANN) and help us create reliable and principled model architecture. Before we move further ahead, generalization error is the difference between training and testing error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central idea of the paper was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Deep neural networks easily fit random labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explicit regularization may improve generalization performance, but is neither necessary nor by itself sufficient for controlling generalization error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;randomization-test---fitting-random-labels-and-pixels&quot;&gt;Randomization Test  : Fitting Random Labels and Pixels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper explained the memorization capacity of the paper through randomizing labels and pixels. Authors trained several standard architectures with randomized labels. They found DNNs easily fit random labels. Moreso, the training error becomes zero, while the testing error is the same as any random chance. Furthering this they experimented with the pixels as well — shuffled pixels, random pixel, and gaussian noise. Surprisingly, stochastic gradient descent with unchanged hyperparameters can optimize weight to fit random labels perfectly. Adding to this astonishment, it was observed that as the noise in the image increases, the generalization error decreases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;explicit-regularization&quot;&gt;Explicit Regularization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explicit regularization techniques like dropout, weight decay, data augmentation are the tools of deep learning. These techniques were tested on random labels. As expected, the results were better. But the point that labels were shuffled makes it difficult to comprehend. Not only this  but implicit regularizers like early stopping also contributed for the betterment of the model trained on shuffled class labels. But we can’t miss that regularizers don’t tamper the weights too much but make subtle changes to make weights more smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all boils down to explain that deep neural networks work on rote memory than on semantic understanding, making neural networks far less interpretable and reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Understanding-Deep-Learning-Requires-Rethinking-Generalization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Understanding-Deep-Learning-Requires-Rethinking-Generalization/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
