<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 11:03:00 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 11:03:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 024, Mechanical Keyboard</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Keychron, Corsair, Razer — THOCK! soothing, satisfying, clickety-clack sounds, we are talking about Mechanical Keyboards. Mechanical Keyboards have become popular in the last decade. You might ask that the ₹500 one does the same thing. This is absolutely true; we can’t deny that the cheap one does the same as the mechanical keyboard. Then why should you invest your money to buy these expensive, custom mechanical keyboards? Because keyboards are essentials we use in everyday life, so like other day-to-day items, why not get something that may potentially better your experience? But what other options do we have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Membrane keyboards, the cheaper keyboards have a layer of silicon rubber matrix between the keys and the PCB. Each key is held with a rubber dome and gets activated only when the key is pressed all the way down to PCB. It is more like hitting your fingers on a hard surface — in the long run, it’s bad for fingers until you want your hands to look like Dr. Strange. But, in mechanical keyboards keys get activated on reaching the actuation point which means you don’t have to push all the way down. The cool thing about mechanical keyboards is their variety and the ability to choose a keyboard which meets your requirements. Variety as in, how the keypress feels, layout, programmability, aesthetics, materials and so on which is very limited to membrane keyboards. Do not want a number pad? Get rid of it; Need dedicated macros? Create them; Want better ergonomics? Get a split or ergonomic keyboard; Do you like the retro look? Just find a retro-looking keyboard or keycaps. It’s all out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just because of mechanical keyboards, instead because of the mechanical switches, which helps in modularity and customisation. This isn’t something you can control with membrane keyboards because they are just a sheet of collapsing domes. But with mechanical keyboards, you can get a range of switches — clicky, tactile, or smooth linear switches, loud, silent whatever you want. Getting something you use in daily life, that feels good, can improve your performance, efficiency and add enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the functional side. The durability of key switches is around 50 million keystrokes which mean mechanical keyboards go for ages. Adding to it, mechanical keyboards are sturdier, heavier and nicely built. The orchestra of CHOK CHOK and CLICK CLICK has added symphony to our gaming, typing and programming experience. Mechanical keyboards are true works of art.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 023, Bright side of quarantine in students life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished two assignments! Oh really? Ok Ok, I copied. This was the closest I can get to college now. I am graduating in 2020, Will I? Who knows? We are the batch of 2020 (if so). While everyone else was ranting about colleges and assignments, I was telling them it’s for their own good. Now it came on me and I feel it’s my responsibility to say a word or two. Is it? No. We are already hammered by the negativity floating on the internet. Instead, we should go somewhere silly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zooms calls have given us the opportunity to attend classes on Pluto, Sun, Golden Gate Bridge, even inside the Pacific Ocean with fishes but my friends chose to study under hanging underwear. Aha! This is how to attain enlightenment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alright, we ain’t getting a graduation party but you can always get high on sanitizer, higher than The Empire States building. JK!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students of engineering college, also known as hunter-gatherers have successfully proved this title wrong. Thanks to home! The control we got on our tongue, otherwise cursing every now and then; the dreams of getting 8 hrs of sleep are now being accomplished daily with the compensation of sleep we missed during Fifa and Sheesha, and all the healthy food instead of rubber butter at college canteen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Although it’s established that I cannot cook but we can cook almost every cuisine at home — we will save money and time. Moreso who found this hobby, please don’t give this up. And to all the restaurants and hotels and college mess, no no not college mess — Fuck You — for forking out money from the pool of our tiny pockets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In other news, the attendance criterion is lifted. We can sleep extra, we can binge-watch the shows and not get overwhelmed by the class the next day, because there are none. But, Netflix and zizz — the most adorable things are becoming boring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To all those people whose birthdays are spent in quarantine, Happy Birthday and Congratulations! You have saved yourself from the brutal birthday bumps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this pandemic is a test of your immunity — immunity to bullshit, immunity to hatred, immunity to selfishness, immunity to indulgence and yes, to a virus. Just hang in there people, 2020 is a rollercoaster ride. We will get through this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 022, Pi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;“3.1415926535… help I am trapped”&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s visit the number land once again — this time for none other than Pi. It is a celebrity number, defined as the ratio of simplest shape, circle, to its diameter. Tech giants compete to calculate the maximum number of digits of Pi. There are competitions of Pi digit memorization. Isn’t it insane that the world record for Pi digits memorization is 100,000? As beautiful as it may sound, uglier it is, the infinite and non-repeating property of Pi, simply leads to mess and madness and chaos. But being transcendental and irrational, isn’t it boring. There are various numbers like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what makes Pi so iconic? Pi is omnipotent. It existed even prior to The Big Bang. The meandering ratio of the river to the orbits of satellites. It’s not just about circles, Pi helps us understand curves, periodic and oscillating systems. It is used in electromagnetics and music as well. In statistics, it is used to measure the area under the bell curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all its applications, Pi is so devoid of patterns that it passes every randomness test with flying colors. It is not only random, but that any string of them occurs just as much as any other of the same length. This means if we encode Pi in base 26, representing each number as alphabets then we can find all of the work of Shakespeare. It would be merely absurd to question at which decimal position. Doesn’t it amuse you, that such an elementary formula gives rise to such a plethora of information? Moreover, Pi opens up the window for transcendental numbers. Most of the numbers on the number line are transcendental, and we have rarely visited that road. This implies how limited human knowledge is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do we calculate Pi? We can’t tell the exact value of Pi but only approximate. The first recorded algorithm to rigorously calculate Pi was Polygon Approximation. Mathematicians inscribed and circumscribed the polygon around a unit circle and thereby calculated the perimeter of both the hugging polygons to find the lower and upper bound of the Pi. Later, this was revolutionized by converging infinite sums. Now in the age of technology, we can calculate the value of Pi with an accuracy within 0.04% through iterative algorithms. What if we calculate the exact value of Pi? Will it be a breakthrough or will it be just another day, who knows? Until then enjoy the chaos of Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Pi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Pi/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 021, Why Socrates hated democracy?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was not even a cohesive empire, it was made up of many city states, led by Athens and Sparta. Despite its fragmentation, it has made innumerous contributions to civilization. Contribution in Mathematics, Medical Science, Astronomy out of which the most prevalent is in Philosophy. Amongst the famous philosophers was Socrates, who lived in the times when democracy was flourishing in Athens. But he was skeptical about the business of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His pessimistic behaviour towards unfettered and pure democracy is described in Plato’s sixth book of &lt;em&gt;The Republic&lt;/em&gt;. Plato dialogued the conversation between Socrates and Adeimantus where Socrates was telling the flaws of democracy by comparing it to a ship. Socrates asked, if you are heading out on a journey in a ship, who would you like to be leading the ship? Just anyone or educated people who fit the role? Adeimantus said the latter of course. In response, Socrates asked why do we keep thinking that any old person should be fit to choose the ruler of the country?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates pointed out voting in an election is a skill, not a random intuition. People must be taught about it systematically like any other skill. Socrates suggested just like maneuvering the ship in a storm, selecting a ruler for the country requires expertise. He was never against the idea everyone should vote. Instead he was worried if the people are educated enough to make this type of decision? Maybe they can be manipulated by the demagogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates knew how easy, people running for election could exploit our desires for easy answers. He asked us to imagine an election between two candidates, one similar to a sweet shop owner and other similar to a doctor. Candidate similar to a sweetshop owner says about the rival, this person gives you injection, asks you to eat bitter medicines and tells you not to eat and drink, but I will give you sweets and candies and ice creams. In response, the doctor did not have much to say but wants to help society. This caused an uproar amongst the voters. Ever Since, we have elected many sweet shop owners and very few doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates insisted that only people who think rationally and deeply about the issues should be allowed to vote. But, as President Abraham Lincoln defined democracy as “Government of the people, by the people, for the people”, are we electing more sweet shop owners or a ruler who wants to make the world a better place. Is it democracy or demagoguery?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Socrates-And-Democracy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Socrates-And-Democracy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 020, Dreams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was doing the most important chore of the day, sleeping, when my mom woke me. Ma, why do you hate me? &lt;em&gt;*Just Kidding&lt;/em&gt;.  Uh-Huh! Lockdown is a party, I am spending more time with my long lost love, sleep — enjoying my pleasure time. Exploring the dimensions through psychic activities in my brain. Aha! Dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seamless realm of dreams is a test site for a myriad of thoughts. But does this dandruff of the brain have any hidden meaning? Moreso, Why did I have that dream? Is it my eating habits? Have I had a lovely day? Something peculiar or am I just overthinking? — Who knows? Even after so many technological advanced studies we still don’t have any definite answer but we have some interesting theories. Our daily routines, aspirations, mood, surroundings make up our dream. We dream to fulfill our wishes. Everything we see in the conscious world has some symbolic meaning which collates to our subconscious desires and anxieties. Dreams let us work through our anxieties in a low-risk environment, helping us practice stressful events and cope with trauma and grief. Dreams edge off the painful experiences to allow for psychological healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dreams can guide us to our unknown parts. It can connect the dots that we cannot in conscious life. We dream to rehearse the dangerous and threatening situations — whether you have an exam the next day or meeting with the President of the United Nations — these dreams allow you to practice your instincts. Unconstrained by reality and by the rules of conventional logic, our brain creates limitless scenarios that help us grasp the situation we are into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember dreams? Neither do I but there are several superstitions regarding them. Psychologists are trying to interpret the meaning of dreams. Mom says Morning dreams often come true. Arab superstition suggests hair falling out or someone cutting hair in dream means you are going to lose money. I never knew about these superstitions, but I ponder how are these dreams interpreted? Probably Psychology, who knows! Dreams are weird. I once had a dream, where I was getting rasgullas for buying clothes — can someone tell me what it means?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who cares? Sweet dreams, wet dreams, seldom very scary dreams — I sleep some more to dream some more.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Dreams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Dreams/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 019, Portal Paradox</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B19nlhbA7-E&quot;&gt;The Portal Paradox&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCUHW94eEFW7hkUMVaZz4eDg&quot;&gt;minutephysics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portal is a hilariously mind-bending game which challenges you to use brains over weapons in a diabolical world of Aperture Science Facility. A young woman, Chell, is forced to solve tests designed by psychopath AI, GLaDOS, using a portal gun with a promise to receive a cake when she solves the puzzle. The player can create portals on ceiling, floor, or wall and move through them instantaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objects in the game, or player themself can pass instantaneously from one end of the portal to another. An object entering one end of the portal at a certain speed leaves the other end at the same speed. The direction of the object leaving the portal depends on the orientation of the other end of the portal. This leads to a paradox — if one end of the portal moves toward the object: does the stationary object simply come out of the portal with zero speed or the object shoots out of the portal with corresponding relative speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, these types of portal do not exist in real life but if they did and obeyed the laws of physics then the question reduces to: if an object has to enter and exit the portal at the same speed then what’s that speed relative to? Velocity is governed in relation to some other object, there is no absolute zero velocity point. This leads us to two options. First, when the object passes through the portal it maintains the same speed relative to the environment though direction may change. Second, the speed of an object, while exiting, is the same as the speed of the portal through which it enters. Another possibility is, the object’s velocity is measured relative to the exit end of the portal. Although the last possibility is quite vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First option which suggests the object remains stationary when entering and exiting the portal seems invalid, because how could a stationary object remain stationary while leaving the portal. The object would have to move. There is a way this option might work, as the cross-section of the object passes through the portal then while exiting, the particles will pile up at the portal as 2D cross-section of the object ensures zero velocity. Moreso, in order to retain the shape and topology of the object the exit portal will act as a wall and the entry portal will bounce off the object prohibiting the exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second option seems more reasonable — velocity of the object is measured relative to the individual ends of the portal. This would be roughly what we expect if the portals are connected to each other through a wormhole then the object would obey the Law of Conservation of Momentum in curved spacetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics point of view suggests that the second option is logical while the designer of the game has opted to otherwise because they are easier to program. Since it is fictional, it’s up to you to decide which approach you would like to follow — the physicists or the programmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look more into it, we bump into more possibilities and numerous questions pop up.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Portal-Paradox/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Portal-Paradox/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 018, Stages of Grief</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just like happiness, Sadness is also a part of human experience. But the idea of sadness is quite convoluted, what it is and what it has to do with anything. It is the natural reaction to any difficult situation, when your loved one dies or your favorite team loses. But the brain deals with it differently. Kubler-Ross in 1969 published her work, On Death and Dying, based on observing and interviewing the patients and people whose close one’s died. Kubler-Ross model modeled grief in 5 stages. Originally it was devised for terminally ill patients but later it was adapted to the loss of other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Denial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bargain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, the five stages of grief do not occur in specific order. We often move between stages before reaching the final stage of acceptance. Moreso, once we know these stages we cannot reach the acceptance any faster. Many of us are not afforded the luxury of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Denial :&lt;/strong&gt; The first reaction when someone learns about the loss — to deny the reality of the situation. It is the common defence mechanism which allows people to absorb the news and begin the process. “This isn’t happening” is a common reaction of people to overwhelming emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anger :&lt;/strong&gt; Next is anger. As the masking effect of denial fades away, we are still not ready for the reality and pain re-emerge. These intense emotions arise from our vulnerable core and are expressed as anger. These emotions may aim at other people and oftentimes inanimate objects. In fact, we often start to blame people who, rationally, shouldn’t be blamed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bargain :&lt;/strong&gt; Being vulnerable and helpless, people try to regain control. Through a series of “if only” and “what if” statements we try to bargain with God to postpone the inevitable, and heal the pain. This defense action helps us postpone sadness, confusion or pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depression :&lt;/strong&gt; The quiet stage. This could be the time when one may embrace and work through the pain in a more healthful manner. The grievous person might isolate themselves from reality in order to completely absorb the pain. But this doesn’t mean depression is easy, it can be difficult and messy like other stages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acceptance :&lt;/strong&gt; And then comes the final stage, acceptance. It is not necessarily a happy stage of grief but it provides one with the truth — the truth about what the grief means to them. It helps you understand the grief and at the end, you finally accept it and continue with your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One moment of grief for all the Indian Cricket fans was when India lost to Pakistan in ICC 2017 Champions Trophy Finals. Every Indian Cricket fan was deeply saddened by the loss and could not believe the scorecard, and Pakistan’s win. As we moved to the next stage, our rage rose against Indian Players and fans started to blame the situations, developed conspiracy theories and whatnot. In order to bargain our grief, we posed different excuses that we won in Hockey by 7-1, at least we reached the finals etc. Slowly phasing into depression and realising we were so close to the cup that we could have won it. Subsequently, most of us accepted that it was a Cricket match and winning and losing is part of the game . Although we still feel bad about whatever happened that day, it’s alright. Indian Cricket Team has made us proud many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone grieves differently. Some people will wear their emotions while others may feel grief internally. At least, You should try and not judge people on how they grief. But the common thread which keeps one through the loss is hope. The key to understanding the stages is not to feel like you must go through each of them. In fact, one should use them as the guides in the grieving process.
&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;As Long As There Is Life, There Is Hope. As Long As There Is Hope, There Is Life.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Stages-of-grief/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Stages-of-grief/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 017, P versus NP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Programmers in the early days of computing started to solve problems using their cabinet size computers. Just like every solution initially, it used to be slow and then improved iteratively. But for some problems they cannot figure out a faster solution while a variety of problems have been proved to have no faster solution, like predicting the optimal move in chess. In order to handle the situation, researchers started sorting programs on how fast the program can solve the problem. Multiplication, Sorting have a faster program while for chess there is no faster program. But there were some problems which couldn’t be determined in which bucket they fell — finding prime numbers, travelling-salesman problem etc. This is where P and NP come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how to figure out that the program is fast in general? Computer Scientists calculate the time for each step and add up. The catch is, they don’t answer this in minutes or seconds, instead they calculate it relative to the number of elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P class of problems are those which can be solved in polynomial time, or the set of problems whose solution time is proportional to polynomial. Obviously, an algorithm whose time is proportional to N&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; is slower than N&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; but this is insignificant when compared to another distinction — the complexity of algorithms where a number is raised to the Nth power, like, 2&lt;sup&gt;N&lt;/sup&gt;. And this discrepancy gets much, much worse as N grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NP — Nondeterministic Polynomial time — is a problem whose solution can be verified in polynomial time. But many of these problems take exponential times to get solved. So what’s the deal with P equal NP? It means if the solution to a problem can be verified in polynomial time, can it be found in polynomial time? Frequently called the most important problem in the computer science domain, P vs NP is one of the 7 problems for which the Clay Mathematics Institute will give you million dollars to (dis)prove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you ponder? There is no specific problem but there are multiple problems in this class. What does that mean? In early 70’s complexity researchers realised that a dozen NP problems they were struggling with are essentially the same but with some polynomial time constraints. You just need to prove one of the problems to make the entire NP set lie inside the P class set. As hard as it is to prove this problem, proving any problem in itself is a NP problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes it so important? 
The excitement to solve this problem is as vivid as the applications it can solve. A lot of the puzzles we are trying to figure out will become easier — the protein folding problem, drug for cancer. We can develop an accurate financial forecasting model,  figure out the optimal arrangement of transistors on a silicon chip and the banking system might collapse as encryptions will become easier to crack.  As &lt;strong&gt;Scott Aaronson&lt;/strong&gt; said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;”If P=NP, then the world would be a profoundly different place than we usually assume it to be. There would be no special value in “creative leaps,” no fundamental gap between solving a problem and recognizing the solution once it's found. Everyone who could appreciate a symphony would be Mozart; everyone who could follow a step-by-step argument would be Gauss; everyone who could recognize a good investment strategy would be Warren Buffett.“&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/P-NP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/P-NP/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 016, Robin: A quintessential Sidekick</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;80 years ago, Robin — the most iconic sidekick, was born. Quirky, witty, comical, bold and badass — this  “Boy Wonder” has risked its life innumerous times while entertaining us. While Bruce Wayne has worn Batman’s cape, there have been many characters behind Robin’s Mask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard John “Dick” Grayson or Robin was debuted in Detective Comics #38, 1940. After the cold-blooded murder of Robin’s parents, by Tony Zucco in order to extort money from the circus that employed them, Robin vowed to take revenge. Witnessing this, Bruce Wayne, a wealthy American playboy, philanthropist by day and vigilante by night, took Robin in and channelized his anger. Batman taught him martial art and trained him as his alter ego to become a crime fighting master. Dick’s successor Jason Todd shared a similar story but due to his negative reception, he was killed, at the hands of Joker, in DC #408 and during the “A death of the Family” storyline. In 2005, he was resurrected as vengeful Red Hood and became a ruthless antihero who clashed with Batman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, Carrie Kelly appeared in Batman: The Dark Knight Returns (1986) which made her the most popular Robin till time. In 1989, Tim Drake, a teen with excellent hacking and technical skill, was trained to become Robin. Stephanie Brown, daughter of villainous Cluemaster, became the first female Robin in mainstream DC continuity in Robin no. 126, who later assumed the role of Batgirl. Lastly, Damian Wayne, son of Talia and Batman fitted into the mantle of Robin. Trained by League of Assassin, when Damian met his father he started to fight for the cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a colorful attire of red, green and yellow tunic, scaly speedos and pixie boots, Robin was inseparable from Batman forming a dynamic duo.  Moreover, Robin is Batman’s best friend and provided him with a family when no one was there. With endless puns, he lightened the dark theme of the comics.  Dick prevented Batman from going too far and reminded him why he chose to fight. Jason mirrored Batman’s own rage, giving him the glimpse of what could have happened if his principles weren’t crude. Tim mirrored Batman’s need for justice while Stephanie showed him how intense his recklessness is. Damian, his own son, has shown him there is a future to the idea despite how bleak the chances are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robins have left a lasting impression on the audience with its comic sense. As the comics grew, each Robin taught Batman something — becoming a perfect sidekick. The legacy of Robin will continue to expand in a positive direction.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Robin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Robin/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 015, Tour de France</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is not just another cycling event but the most prestigious which attracts the world’s best riders. Around 20 teams with eight riders each, the bikers cycle through the steep climbs of the Alps and the Pyrenees to the scorching sun on the flats, from the race against time to the endurance test — Tour de France is the toughest amongst the major sporting events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting off with an aim to sell more copies of sports newspaper L’Auto in 1903. The editor setup the 2400 Km cycling event in 5 stages over the course of 19 days across the country.  Within 5 years their sales doubled. The saddle point which sparked the interest of the spectator was, in 1910 when the riders were sent, for the first time, to the Tourmalet — the highest paved mountain path with a 19km uphill climb ascending 1400m to the summit. 1919 marked the introduction of the yellow jersey, because L’Auto was published on Yellow paper. This jersey also known as Maillot Jaune is an honor given to the rider with least cumulative time. Three other types of jersey are also awarded during the tour. Green jersey, also known as Maillot Vert is awarded to the best sprinter; Polka Dot jersey to the finest climber and the White Jersey to best-placed rider aged under 26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each rider wearing colors of their national jersey, this colorful combination forms a kaleidoscope of moving color on wheels known as Peloton — which saves energy of the riders at the back. The riders in the front protect the riders at the back by cutting the wind resistance, helping the best team member to  perform better in later parts of the tour. This technique of forming a peloton is known as Drafting. The scenic views of Tour de France might sound picturesque but it is the toughest of all major sporting events. The riders burn up to 7000 calories per day, while ordinarily a person burns 2000 calories per day. Their heartbeats go up to 200 BPM. And god forbid the weather. Cyclists might catch the common cold in the winds, rain, hail and even snow on the mountain. In flats, the blistering heat and the sun cause chronic dehydration and fatigue. If you still feel it’s easy, then try to cycle at 300 Watts for 2 km, you might feel the burn. Professionals, on an average generate more than 400 Watts of energy during the tour. Cherry on top, the tour gets a little tougher every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, the event has been postponed due to COVID-19 and will now start on August 29, 2020 at Nice, France and the race will end on 20 September 2020 in Paris. During the 23 days of the event the riders cycle for 21 days while resting for 2 days.The cyclist journeys through more mountains and climbs, making it more dangerous, through the scenic plains to race for the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tour de France isn’t about the strongest rider but one who endures the most pain, physically and mentally,  and ultimately has what it takes to conquer the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Tour-de-France/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Tour-de-France/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
