<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 02:00:59 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 02:00:59 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 028, Honey Bees</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Honey Bees are the most collaborative species in the world. Each hive comprises thousands of bees working together in order to build and sustain the colony. Within the colony, each bee is assigned with a role. Queen’s job is simple — she creates the foundation of the beehive and lay eggs for future generations. There is usually a single queen in the hive. Also, queen bees have the duty to regulate the hive’s activities. Worker bees are female bees who take care of housekeeping of the hive, foraging, feeding the queen bee and drones, taking care of larvae, and collecting pollen and nectar. They work so hard that their life span is around 6 weeks. And lastly, the drones are male bees whose main role is to mate. They are most active during spring and summer and die as winter approaches. Fun fact is that male bee can mate only once and dies soon after it. This is because the ejaculation is so strong that it ruptures endophallus, leaving the bulb of endophallus inside the queen bee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a brain the size of a seed, how do bees have such great work ethics? It is part of their genes and it starts with the queen bee who has the unique ability to designate the sex of her children. Besides this, bees are excellent mathematicians, they can calculate angles and also comprehend the roundness of the earth. But the most important mathematical marvel in honey bees’ life is their hive. The design of the hive is perfect. Bees need a safe place to secure their entire colony and a place to store nectar which will ripe into honey. For this, they need some serious space optimization. They use honey wax to make the hive. But the problem is that a single ounce of honey wax is produced from eight ounces of honey. In order to minimize their work and design a safe and spacious hive, they develop Hexagonal structure — this uses the least amount of honey wax, provides the most amount of space and  also provides a sturdier structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The honeycomb structure isn’t the only contribution of Honey Bees. They produce honey, a sugary syrup with medicinal property. Bees eat insects that damage crop like mites, spiders and also help in pollination. Moreso, One out of three meals eaten by humans is made possible because of honey bees. They help winemakers by biting grapes and kickstarting fermentation. If all honey bees die, the plant will slowly start to deteriorate leading to starvation of millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey bees are disappearing at a very rapid rate. Disease, parasite or starvation doesn’t conclude to this cause, there is more to it. This mysterious disappearance of bees is known as Colony Collapse Disorder. Despite the fact that scientists do not surely know the exact reason, they have suggested : Pesticides and chemicals, depriving queen bees’ immunity due to hybridization of bees to produce honey on commercial levels, stress because of human activities and many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey bees are now fighting for survival. It would be a catastrophe if they lost this fight. This is a conundrum we have to solve if we want to continue to live with an abundance and diversity of food. We are deeply connected to other life forms and we have to take better care of our surroundings — if not for the beauty of nature but at least for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Honey-Bees/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Honey-Bees/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 027, Onion Peel Experiment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Woohoo! Finally, we were going to visit the Biology Lab. Class 9 was an innocuous period — Little did we know, little did we bother. Just like any other day, I dressed up and cycled my way to school. Bell rang and It was our biology class and the teacher entered the class. Professor Afsar Khan had a weird personality — witty and strict at the same time. We never understood if we should laugh at his jokes or not. If we did he might scold us and if we didn’t we might disrespect his joke. Despite this, he was a brilliant teacher. But an unusual thing happened as he entered the class, while we were taking out our notebooks he asked us to pack our bags. At first, we were confused because he has never asked us to do so but later we thought he would take us to the ground and we will play. Instead, we were going to perform an experiment — Onion Peel Experiment — in the Biology Lab. And, for those of you who don’t know, it was our first time in any kind of laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The silence of our class broke out and it seemed like a fish market — everyone was super excited, but our teacher had a dead look on his face. In a matter of seconds, we formed a queue, which otherwise used to take an eternity, and jollily marched through the corridor. And as a matter of fact, for students of boys school, we behaved the best. No one jumped the queue, none stopped for toilet or water break, and even the disinterested students were gleaming. As we approached the laboratory, our Lab Assistant unlocked the lab. As soon as we had a glimpse of the lab, our jaws dropped. We did not expect anything like that in our old school building but little did we know, we never saw a lab before. It seemed like Potions class from Harry Potter, there were jars of different specimens all around us. Skeleton hung by the wall, there were diagrams of plant and animal reproductive parts. Boys started to conspire about all of them and came up with the most unlikely theories and ambitions. However silly they seem now, they all made sense in 9th standard. I vividly remember one, a friend of mine claimed, on seeing a brain inside a jar, that the brain belonged to Albert Einstein which left us all in awe. While we were extending our eyes as far as we could, Professor Afsar grabbed our attention and started to explain the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asked us to take a piece of chopped onion and told us that the lab assistant will provide tools. Professor Afsar asked us to start performing the experiment but everyone was blankly staring at each other because we were so deeply engulfed that anyone barely cared to listen. There was awkwardness in the environment and our teachers could sense it and they loved to feed on it, so did Professor Afsar. He gave us a piece of his mind, but he explained it to us again. We were asked to take off onion peel, place it on watch glass, then add safranin and let it soak. Then wash the peel with water, soak it in extra water, add a drop of glycerine and then examine it under the microscope to observe the plant cell. It might seem simple now, but we found an opportunity to mischief at each step. Aware of the danger that Professor is watching, we fought for a bigger onion piece with a tweezer as our sword and watch glass as our shield. In another corner of the laboratory, students were pinching each other with a tweezer, some of the students tried to create music by clicking tweezers together. The impressive thing was that Professor Afsar did not lose his cool, it seemed like he had already experienced all of this earlier as well. Once in a while, he took a check on us and taunted us for not doing any work. As the class was about to get over, he created two watch glasses and put it under two microscopes because we all were too busy with our own stupidity. He asked us to form two queues and look at the onion peel through the microscope. No one understood what they were looking at and what was the purpose of it. Everyone was having the time of their life while some students were still in line and the bell rang. Students in the queue looked disappointed but Professor Afsar allowed them to fulfill their wishes to look into nothingness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We packed our bags and walked back to classes as if we had just performed a surgery. This was the most fulfilling day of our school life.
And Period.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Onion-Peel-Experiment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Onion-Peel-Experiment/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 026, Over-the-top (OTT) media services</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The innovation of moving frames was invented by Lumière Brothers and today we are in the age of Netflix, Disney+, Hotstar etc. The technology of cinema has evolved. Things changed from the black and white moving images to hours of UltraHD video footage with binaural noise to movies that have a whole lot of visual effects to movies made of computer-generated images. In terms of technology, first came the television age, then a lot of private channels which brought in a lot more entertainment, then came the era of CDs and DVDs and finally the advent of broadband gave way to Over-the-top media services and now we can stream the movie that we want, the show that we want, the documentary that we want anytime, anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The streaming revolution is here — the next great leap in how the world gets its entertainment is here.  With thousands of hours of content on OTT platforms, this age can be termed as the golden age of OTT. OTTs are doing more than evolving the TV format; OTT is growing, both for consumers and advertisers. For consumers, the accessibility of the content on multiple screens anytime and anywhere makes it more engaging. And advertisers can show personalized advertisements. Also, OTT platforms often help in the production of numerous movies, shows and documentaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the boom in network technologies and internet speed, people have started to consume more content. Customers are slowly cutting off their cable connection and switching to OTT platforms. OTTs provide the consumer to view specified content despite Television. The subscription-based media consumption provides an abundance of particular media streams through one channel while television provides a plethora of channels to view but a limited number of options of a particular genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OTTs are evolving as well. With every new feature they add to their platform, other platforms try to incorporate it to make more monetary benefits. In the fiscal year 2019, OTT platforms in India had a market value of ₹3500 crores and slowly the market is expanding. We don’t know what the future of streaming looks like but we surely know it will provide a diversity of streams on a given platform.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/OTTs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/OTTs/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 025, N-Queen Problem </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Chess is a game of multi facets and has lots of mysteries with each piece. One piece, in particular, assumed to be most powerful right after the king, the queen has made up a puzzle, the N-queens problem —  try to place N queens on a N\(\times\)N chessboard so that none of the queens attacks each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially devised for the 8\(\times\)8 chess, that is to place queens such that none attack each other. The problem to find all the solutions to the 8-Queen problem is computationally expensive as there are &lt;sub&gt;64&lt;/sub&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; (= 4,42,61,65,368) possibilities out of which there are only 92 solutions. Is there a solution better than brute force? Given the constraints of Queens’ move, we can narrow down the possibilities. If we consider the straight movement of the queen we can narrow down the number to 8&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; (= 1,67,77,216) which can be further punched down to 8! =(40,320) by permuting the diagonal move of the queen. Out of the 92 solutions mentioned, if we do not consider symmetry operation of reflection and rotation then we are left with only 12 solutions. But as N goes up, the value of N! goes up and causes trouble of computability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this time complexity can be optimized by using backtracking algorithms. Backtracking is a recursive process where the queen is placed on the edge and ideally saves the possible attacks. Then another queen is placed at a safe position and the process is repeated. However, if the N queens cannot be placed at safe positions then the algorithm backtracks and then try another safe position. This takes around 2&lt;sup&gt;N&lt;/sup&gt; steps in the worst case which is 100 times faster than the brute-force algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can still speed up the algorithm on the cost of storage. Known as Branch and Bound, this algorithm is similar to backtracking (described in the previous paragraph) but keeps a track of the state of the board to prevent any unnecessary recursion. There are numerous other algorithms, some more efficient, others less but none of the algorithms has helped to cross the barrier to place 26 safe queens on 26\(\times\)26 chessboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreso, as the size of the board increases, the number of solutions to place the queens increases exponentially. Funnily,  for 5\(\times\)5 boards there are 10 distinct solutions and for 6\(\times\)6 boards the number of solutions drops to 4. There is no formula to calculate the number of solutions nor can we figure out the asymptotic limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the N-queen problem, several other puzzles emerge from chessboard like knights’ tours. I sometimes wonder if we can ever explore all the possible states of a chessboard and come up with new puzzles, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Queen-Problem/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Queen-Problem/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 024, Mechanical Keyboard</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Keychron, Corsair, Razer — THOCK! soothing, satisfying, clickety-clack sounds, we are talking about Mechanical Keyboards. Mechanical Keyboards have become popular in the last decade. You might ask that the ₹500 one does the same thing. This is absolutely true; we can’t deny that the cheap one does the same as the mechanical keyboard. Then why should you invest your money to buy these expensive, custom mechanical keyboards? Because keyboards are essentials we use in everyday life, so like other day-to-day items, why not get something that may potentially better your experience? But what other options do we have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Membrane keyboards, the cheaper keyboards have a layer of silicon rubber matrix between the keys and the PCB. Each key is held with a rubber dome and gets activated only when the key is pressed all the way down to PCB. It is more like hitting your fingers on a hard surface — in the long run, it’s bad for fingers until you want your hands to look like Dr. Strange. But, in mechanical keyboards keys get activated on reaching the actuation point which means you don’t have to push all the way down. The cool thing about mechanical keyboards is their variety and the ability to choose a keyboard which meets your requirements. Variety as in, how the keypress feels, layout, programmability, aesthetics, materials and so on which is very limited to membrane keyboards. Do not want a number pad? Get rid of it; Need dedicated macros? Create them; Want better ergonomics? Get a split or ergonomic keyboard; Do you like the retro look? Just find a retro-looking keyboard or keycaps. It’s all out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just because of mechanical keyboards, instead because of the mechanical switches, which helps in modularity and customisation. This isn’t something you can control with membrane keyboards because they are just a sheet of collapsing domes. But with mechanical keyboards, you can get a range of switches — clicky, tactile, or smooth linear switches, loud, silent whatever you want. Getting something you use in daily life, that feels good, can improve your performance, efficiency and add enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the functional side. The durability of key switches is around 50 million keystrokes which mean mechanical keyboards go for ages. Adding to it, mechanical keyboards are sturdier, heavier and nicely built. The orchestra of CHOK CHOK and CLICK CLICK has added symphony to our gaming, typing and programming experience. Mechanical keyboards are true works of art.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 023, Bright side of quarantine in students life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished two assignments! Oh really? Ok Ok, I copied. This was the closest I can get to college now. I am graduating in 2020, Will I? Who knows? We are the batch of 2020 (if so). While everyone else was ranting about colleges and assignments, I was telling them it’s for their own good. Now it came on me and I feel it’s my responsibility to say a word or two. Is it? No. We are already hammered by the negativity floating on the internet. Instead, we should go somewhere silly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zooms calls have given us the opportunity to attend classes on Pluto, Sun, Golden Gate Bridge, even inside the Pacific Ocean with fishes but my friends chose to study under hanging underwear. Aha! This is how to attain enlightenment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alright, we ain’t getting a graduation party but you can always get high on sanitizer, higher than The Empire States building. JK!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students of engineering college, also known as hunter-gatherers have successfully proved this title wrong. Thanks to home! The control we got on our tongue, otherwise cursing every now and then; the dreams of getting 8 hrs of sleep are now being accomplished daily with the compensation of sleep we missed during Fifa and Sheesha, and all the healthy food instead of rubber butter at college canteen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Although it’s established that I cannot cook but we can cook almost every cuisine at home — we will save money and time. Moreso who found this hobby, please don’t give this up. And to all the restaurants and hotels and college mess, no no not college mess — Fuck You — for forking out money from the pool of our tiny pockets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In other news, the attendance criterion is lifted. We can sleep extra, we can binge-watch the shows and not get overwhelmed by the class the next day, because there are none. But, Netflix and zizz — the most adorable things are becoming boring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To all those people whose birthdays are spent in quarantine, Happy Birthday and Congratulations! You have saved yourself from the brutal birthday bumps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this pandemic is a test of your immunity — immunity to bullshit, immunity to hatred, immunity to selfishness, immunity to indulgence and yes, to a virus. Just hang in there people, 2020 is a rollercoaster ride. We will get through this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 022, Pi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;“3.1415926535… help I am trapped”&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s visit the number land once again — this time for none other than Pi. It is a celebrity number, defined as the ratio of simplest shape, circle, to its diameter. Tech giants compete to calculate the maximum number of digits of Pi. There are competitions of Pi digit memorization. Isn’t it insane that the world record for Pi digits memorization is 100,000? As beautiful as it may sound, uglier it is, the infinite and non-repeating property of Pi, simply leads to mess and madness and chaos. But being transcendental and irrational, isn’t it boring. There are various numbers like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what makes Pi so iconic? Pi is omnipotent. It existed even prior to The Big Bang. The meandering ratio of the river to the orbits of satellites. It’s not just about circles, Pi helps us understand curves, periodic and oscillating systems. It is used in electromagnetics and music as well. In statistics, it is used to measure the area under the bell curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all its applications, Pi is so devoid of patterns that it passes every randomness test with flying colors. It is not only random, but that any string of them occurs just as much as any other of the same length. This means if we encode Pi in base 26, representing each number as alphabets then we can find all of the work of Shakespeare. It would be merely absurd to question at which decimal position. Doesn’t it amuse you, that such an elementary formula gives rise to such a plethora of information? Moreover, Pi opens up the window for transcendental numbers. Most of the numbers on the number line are transcendental, and we have rarely visited that road. This implies how limited human knowledge is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do we calculate Pi? We can’t tell the exact value of Pi but only approximate. The first recorded algorithm to rigorously calculate Pi was Polygon Approximation. Mathematicians inscribed and circumscribed the polygon around a unit circle and thereby calculated the perimeter of both the hugging polygons to find the lower and upper bound of the Pi. Later, this was revolutionized by converging infinite sums. Now in the age of technology, we can calculate the value of Pi with an accuracy within 0.04% through iterative algorithms. What if we calculate the exact value of Pi? Will it be a breakthrough or will it be just another day, who knows? Until then enjoy the chaos of Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Pi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Pi/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 021, Why Socrates hated democracy?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was not even a cohesive empire, it was made up of many city states, led by Athens and Sparta. Despite its fragmentation, it has made innumerous contributions to civilization. Contribution in Mathematics, Medical Science, Astronomy out of which the most prevalent is in Philosophy. Amongst the famous philosophers was Socrates, who lived in the times when democracy was flourishing in Athens. But he was skeptical about the business of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His pessimistic behaviour towards unfettered and pure democracy is described in Plato’s sixth book of &lt;em&gt;The Republic&lt;/em&gt;. Plato dialogued the conversation between Socrates and Adeimantus where Socrates was telling the flaws of democracy by comparing it to a ship. Socrates asked, if you are heading out on a journey in a ship, who would you like to be leading the ship? Just anyone or educated people who fit the role? Adeimantus said the latter of course. In response, Socrates asked why do we keep thinking that any old person should be fit to choose the ruler of the country?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates pointed out voting in an election is a skill, not a random intuition. People must be taught about it systematically like any other skill. Socrates suggested just like maneuvering the ship in a storm, selecting a ruler for the country requires expertise. He was never against the idea everyone should vote. Instead he was worried if the people are educated enough to make this type of decision? Maybe they can be manipulated by the demagogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates knew how easy, people running for election could exploit our desires for easy answers. He asked us to imagine an election between two candidates, one similar to a sweet shop owner and other similar to a doctor. Candidate similar to a sweetshop owner says about the rival, this person gives you injection, asks you to eat bitter medicines and tells you not to eat and drink, but I will give you sweets and candies and ice creams. In response, the doctor did not have much to say but wants to help society. This caused an uproar amongst the voters. Ever Since, we have elected many sweet shop owners and very few doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates insisted that only people who think rationally and deeply about the issues should be allowed to vote. But, as President Abraham Lincoln defined democracy as “Government of the people, by the people, for the people”, are we electing more sweet shop owners or a ruler who wants to make the world a better place. Is it democracy or demagoguery?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Socrates-And-Democracy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Socrates-And-Democracy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 020, Dreams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was doing the most important chore of the day, sleeping, when my mom woke me. Ma, why do you hate me? &lt;em&gt;*Just Kidding&lt;/em&gt;.  Uh-Huh! Lockdown is a party, I am spending more time with my long lost love, sleep — enjoying my pleasure time. Exploring the dimensions through psychic activities in my brain. Aha! Dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seamless realm of dreams is a test site for a myriad of thoughts. But does this dandruff of the brain have any hidden meaning? Moreso, Why did I have that dream? Is it my eating habits? Have I had a lovely day? Something peculiar or am I just overthinking? — Who knows? Even after so many technological advanced studies we still don’t have any definite answer but we have some interesting theories. Our daily routines, aspirations, mood, surroundings make up our dream. We dream to fulfill our wishes. Everything we see in the conscious world has some symbolic meaning which collates to our subconscious desires and anxieties. Dreams let us work through our anxieties in a low-risk environment, helping us practice stressful events and cope with trauma and grief. Dreams edge off the painful experiences to allow for psychological healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dreams can guide us to our unknown parts. It can connect the dots that we cannot in conscious life. We dream to rehearse the dangerous and threatening situations — whether you have an exam the next day or meeting with the President of the United Nations — these dreams allow you to practice your instincts. Unconstrained by reality and by the rules of conventional logic, our brain creates limitless scenarios that help us grasp the situation we are into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember dreams? Neither do I but there are several superstitions regarding them. Psychologists are trying to interpret the meaning of dreams. Mom says Morning dreams often come true. Arab superstition suggests hair falling out or someone cutting hair in dream means you are going to lose money. I never knew about these superstitions, but I ponder how are these dreams interpreted? Probably Psychology, who knows! Dreams are weird. I once had a dream, where I was getting rasgullas for buying clothes — can someone tell me what it means?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who cares? Sweet dreams, wet dreams, seldom very scary dreams — I sleep some more to dream some more.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Dreams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Dreams/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 019, Portal Paradox</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B19nlhbA7-E&quot;&gt;The Portal Paradox&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCUHW94eEFW7hkUMVaZz4eDg&quot;&gt;minutephysics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portal is a hilariously mind-bending game which challenges you to use brains over weapons in a diabolical world of Aperture Science Facility. A young woman, Chell, is forced to solve tests designed by psychopath AI, GLaDOS, using a portal gun with a promise to receive a cake when she solves the puzzle. The player can create portals on ceiling, floor, or wall and move through them instantaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objects in the game, or player themself can pass instantaneously from one end of the portal to another. An object entering one end of the portal at a certain speed leaves the other end at the same speed. The direction of the object leaving the portal depends on the orientation of the other end of the portal. This leads to a paradox — if one end of the portal moves toward the object: does the stationary object simply come out of the portal with zero speed or the object shoots out of the portal with corresponding relative speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, these types of portal do not exist in real life but if they did and obeyed the laws of physics then the question reduces to: if an object has to enter and exit the portal at the same speed then what’s that speed relative to? Velocity is governed in relation to some other object, there is no absolute zero velocity point. This leads us to two options. First, when the object passes through the portal it maintains the same speed relative to the environment though direction may change. Second, the speed of an object, while exiting, is the same as the speed of the portal through which it enters. Another possibility is, the object’s velocity is measured relative to the exit end of the portal. Although the last possibility is quite vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First option which suggests the object remains stationary when entering and exiting the portal seems invalid, because how could a stationary object remain stationary while leaving the portal. The object would have to move. There is a way this option might work, as the cross-section of the object passes through the portal then while exiting, the particles will pile up at the portal as 2D cross-section of the object ensures zero velocity. Moreso, in order to retain the shape and topology of the object the exit portal will act as a wall and the entry portal will bounce off the object prohibiting the exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second option seems more reasonable — velocity of the object is measured relative to the individual ends of the portal. This would be roughly what we expect if the portals are connected to each other through a wormhole then the object would obey the Law of Conservation of Momentum in curved spacetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics point of view suggests that the second option is logical while the designer of the game has opted to otherwise because they are easier to program. Since it is fictional, it’s up to you to decide which approach you would like to follow — the physicists or the programmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look more into it, we bump into more possibilities and numerous questions pop up.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Portal-Paradox/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Portal-Paradox/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
