<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 02:02:24 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 02:02:24 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.7</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 053, Slo-Mo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you watched The Matrix, then you must vividly remember The government Lobby shootout scene — it is rated as the best slow motion action shot. These shots are added to make the scene more theatrical and intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow Motion refers to the effect in videos where time appears to be slowed down. The idea is very simple but the fundamentals are counter-intuitive. High-speed cameras make things appear to move slowly. High-speed cameras have the feature of high frame rate. We often view a video at 24 frames per second. What would happen if you view a very fast frame rate video at a slower rate? Right! It will appear to become slow. Perhaps, we can play a 24 FPS video to some lower rate, let’s say 6 FPS, then the video will become one-fourth times slower than the actual video. But it will definitely lack the fluidity. We can achieve the real sense of slow-mo by using a really expensive shooting device or using post processing softwares. The feat of technology has allowed us to shoot slow-mo videos on our phone. Then again we also have techniques to speed up the video, this process is known as “undercranking”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because it is shot at a higher frame rate, the shutter speed is high, thus less light hits the sensor of the camera. This makes the whole video dark. To compensate for it, ISO is boosted. Which is why there is noise when you shoot a slo-mo on your phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is this cinematic technique of slow-mo so intoxicating? Slow-mo is often used to portray how you would perceive the world when on adrenaline high. Slo-Mo helps in discovering the intricacies of the scene and more importantly it is so powerful that it can make you forget everything else in the scene. It accentuates the feeling, action, effect and phenomenon. Being slow, there is a subtle feeling of sadness and intenseness. It has the ability to enhance the drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From photography to slow motion videos, this is not just a feat of technology but an aesthetic tool for storytelling be it movies or sports or house party.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Slo-mo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Slo-mo/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 052, Neuroscience of Depression</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of the Youtube &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F6qwVcrQB2E&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/a&gt; by Tanmay Bhat, Kaneez Surkha, Abish Mathew and Dr. Siddharth Warrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think when you hear the term depression? A feeling of sadness and unhappiness. Everyone feels low and more importantly everyone’s experience is different. Depression is a medical problem. Although there is a lot to learn in the dimension of depression, there are certain criteria that help in identifying and treating depression. Clinical depression is diagnosed if a person has 5 or more of the 9 undermentioned symptoms for more than 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feel unhappy, sad, or miserable nearly every day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feel helpless, hopeless, or worthless&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lose interest in hobbies, friends, and activities that used to give pleasure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t sleep well or sleep too much&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gain or lose weight without efforts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are constantly tired or have low energy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a hard time concentrating or making decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inability to feel pleasure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Losing Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can enter this vicious spiral of depression through any of these symptoms and then one might lead to another. It is very common, 1 in 10 people will have it in their lifetime. But the problem with depression is — there are symptoms and triggers; trauma, stress, hormonal imbalance; but there is no measure and tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the roots of depression, we must first understand the primitiveness of the brain — the idea of pleasure and pain. The survival instinct of all the animals is based on reward and punishment. Fear prevents us from doing things that might hurt us while pleasure does otherwise. The core of the brain or the limbic system responds to pleasure and pain. But as we evolve we add layers to our brain. This helps us in making more radical decisions. Furthermore, this complex sense adds wants (pleasure) and likes (happiness) to our emotion system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depression is all the same as happiness with something wrong in the circuitry. The happiness circuitry has DorsoLateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC) which is the executive center, for planning and decision making; secondly an area for self awareness, this comprises of Orbitofrontal Cortex (OFC) and Insula and the third component being limbic system which forms the foundation of emotions. OFC and Insula decide who you are as a person and send messages to DLPFC. While the limbic system, on the basis of memories stored in the hippocampus, sets emotions. If these actions, motivations and emotions are symphonized then we feel happiness and if they aren’t in sync then pain — reward and punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While depressed our brain starts to sense punishment more. Certain changes happen in the brain. DLPFC shrink, leading to unwillingness to do things, losing concentration and then developing apathy. Gradually, the hippocampus starts to shrink as well — can’t remember things. All along, during depression we feel threatened. This chronic threat is considered an infection. To address this our body releases cytokines to kill the bacterias and viruses — but there aren’t any. Insula which keeps the statistics of the body is surrounded by cytokines. Once this happens, the body starts to feel sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[Depression\;= \;Sign\,of\,Sickness\;-\;Infection\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DLPFC is already not doing anything, Insula is surrounded by cytokines and doesn’t give any order. This makes us go down the loop towards a darker dimension. There are Non-pharmacological as well as pharmacological treatments to break this loop. Non-pharmacological includes Cognitive Behavioral Therapy, Yoga and Meditation while pharmacological includes medications like serotonin. The healing process also takes place in a loop. But this process might spiral back if there is no one to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are taught to be kind to people. Who knows what might trigger someone and lead them down the vicious spiral and drench them in self-loathe, anxiety, stress. Infact, your act of kindness might help the depressed person to be optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ah, kindness. What a simple way to tell another struggling soul that there is love to be found in the world.” ― Alison Malee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Neuroscience-of-Depression/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Neuroscience-of-Depression/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 051, IIT Hyderabad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, during the summer break I went to IIT Hyderabad for my internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30 km from the main city, lay concrete marvel. Nevertheless, it was still under construction and would take around 10 years to complete. I reached the college around 8 PM, got my room allotted and unpacked my stuff. I was lost, nervous but excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/iith.jpg&quot; height=&quot;90%&quot; width=&quot;90%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;An Evening at IIT Hyderabad&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day, I met my PhD mentor, Charantej Reddy Pochimreddy, while my guide was not available. In the meantime, Charan gave me a tour of the lab, and the work they do at the lab. They aimed mainly towards signal processing and theoretical understanding of neural networks. Also, they studied adversarial machine learning. Charan suggested some readings and asked me to make a list of all the ideas and formulate a research proposal for them. For the rest of the day, I explored &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cleverhans.io/&quot;&gt;cleverhans.io&lt;/a&gt;, to explore the dimensions of adversarial machine learning. Next day, I met Prof. Aditya Siripuram and showed him the proposal. He suggested application based project instead of diving into theoretical approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after rigorous first principle questioning, we developed an idea where we have to generate the training dataset of a black box classifier. Charan’s experience was quite helpful, he had submitted some research papers. Initial readings were based on decision trees and forming fuzzy images. We scraped some more papers and found out a really fascinating GAN based architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My daily routine revolved within mess-lab-mess-lab-mess-room. Soon I met Divyansh Tiwari, another intern from Jabalpur, who first thought I was a M. Tech. student. As usual, I was running late and so was Divyansh. Day in day out, Divyansh became my first friend at IIT Hyderabad and his gang — Sonam, a mechanical engineering intern; Kailash, a skeptical athletic civil engineering intern and Chirag, another mechanical engineer intern. Chirag and Sonam worked under the same professor. On June 20, Kakul Shrivastava aka Shrini came to IIT Hyderabad for the internship, a hardworking introvert. For those who don’t know, Kakul is from ZHCET AMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, Our project was slowly blooming. I aimed to develop an architecture similar to Generative Adversarial Network to learn the feature space of the classifier. The classifier identified between the images of Orlando Bloom and Keira Knightley. Once the classifier was trained, we attached it in parallel to the discriminator. The weights of the Classifier were fixed. To understand the feature space of the classifier, we devised weighted loss. A dynamic scaling factor was introduced. As the image is developed by a generator, we pass it through a discriminator and classifier. The loss through discriminator was multiplied by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/code&gt; while the loss from classifier through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1-alpha&lt;/code&gt; and then back propagated. Initially &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/code&gt; was set to be 1, and it changed as the model got better. This was to make sure that the classifier acted as the discriminator. Now, that the whole foundation was laid, our aim was to stabilize the GAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst, I enjoyed the peaceful life — a chill, sobriety. Enjoying 3 free coffees daily at Shiru’s Cafe and having endless discussions about the weirdness of the shape of the building. Finally, other interns left. Me and Kakul were left. Interestingly, we both worked on the same floor in two different labs at diagonally opposite ends. We used to share breakfast, lunch, dinner and evening coffee. It was fun. She is one of the greatest friends I ever had, I bonded quite well with her, she is always available to help. She is like the President of Happy Club, no expectation, no demands. Probably the nicest person I have met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my project wasn’t sailing so smoothly. GANs are very hard to stabilize. The most fragile neural networks I have ever played with. Even a slight change in a factor and GANs flip out. For most of the time, I tried to stabilize GAN and clean our data. For a month or so I tried to fix the three very basic problems of GAN: Mode Collapse, Diminished Gradient and Non Convergence. To fix this, I tried the Wasserstein GANs, Wasserstein GAN with Gradient Penalty, Energy Based GANs, Spectral Normalization GAN. Most of the time I could address only 2 of the 3 specified problem. But while working with Spectral Normalization GAN, there was a substantial improvement in the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon I had to leave — the vibe, the calmness, the food, the melancholy and most importantly the late night show with Kakul. We both were going to meet in college but….
Period.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/IITH/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/IITH/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 050, Emoji — 😀 😒 🤥 💀  👾 🤖 🎃 😺</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, July 17 was Emoji Day. So I decided to write about it. July 17 is marked as emoji day because Apple calendar emoji has the same date mentioned on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cave paintings to emoji — we have come a long way. With every passing day, as we evolve new emojis are introduced. Emojis are the future of language and semiotics. Much like punctuations, emoji’s have made the conversations hasslefree. Well, thinking about conversation without emoji is difficult for us. Emoji makes the conversation interesting and helps us to express ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, there were emoticons — :-) and :-( and :-P. For the most part, they were used in chat rooms in the 1990s. The first emoji was created by Japanese artist Shigetaka Kurita in 1999. Kurita wanted to design an attractive interface to convey information in a simple way. So Kurita sketched 12-by-12 pixel images that could be selected from the keyboard-like grid and then sent on to mobile and pages. Kurita’s original 176 emoji’s — now part of the permanent collection of the New York Museum of Modern Art — had symbols to characterise emotions, weather, traffic, technology and phases of the moon. As of March 2020, Unicode Consortium — which acts as the UN for text and signs — has approved 3304 emojis. Now more than 92 percent of the people online use emoji, and one-third use on a daily basis. This trend of emoji began when Apple added emojis to iOS keyboard in 2008. Two years later, Android also unveiled an emoji keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the language of texting changed. In 2015, Oxford Dictionary crowned “Face with Tears of Joy” as the word of the year. This was the first time that an emoji became a linguistic champion. Meanwhile All the emojis are pixels of information. Emoji roots from the Japanese word “e” which means picture and “moji” which means character. Essentially, the emojis are images designed to narrate a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year designers submit new emojis to the Unicode Consortium which are properly testified before being rolled out. The fundamental improvement in the emoji vocabulary is based on the incorporation of culture of underrepresented communities. As these emojis come up we understand something about the cultural priorities and types of people who are included in forming this digital growing age. Anyone can submit a proposal to add a new emoji. Unicode asks for proper documentation, an explanation of why and how people will use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Text is the most powerful, go-to communication tool. Emojis are the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Emoji/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Emoji/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 049, Diamonds</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From the mines of Aikhal, Russia to the hands of your loved ones. “A diamond is forever” — De Beers, during the diamond monopoly, made it the epitome of love. The marketing tactic by De Beers has made diamonds reach the mark they are at now. Once they monopolized the diamond market, they soon controlled its supply. Often this marketing campaign is considered as the most successful campaign ever. Believe me, diamonds are not investments. They re-sell at 25-30% of their actual worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree, unlike several other gems, Diamonds are forged deep inside the Earth’s crust under very high pressure and temperature which makes it rare and hence making it expensive. But given the technological advancements diamond can be fabricated in the lab as well. Diamond is an allotrope of carbon just like graphite. But they both have different atom alignment which gives them different properties. In the lab, graphite is exposed to hundreds of tonnes of pressure which converts graphite to diamond. Compared to the diamonds formed under the earth’s crust, the diamonds formed in the lab are crystal clear and are aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do diamonds surface? Diamonds are formed 100-150 km beneath the earth’s surface and reside at volcanic magma chambers. When a volcano erupts, a rare type of magma, kimberlite, is erupted which when cooled form diamonds. These diamonds age between 1 billion to 3.5 billion years.  But these diamonds have impurities which are introduced in the lattice when they are being formed. Although these discrepancies make them ugly, they are very useful for scientists. These inconsistencies help in understanding and advancing the study of deeper earth. These marvels of the natural world have the highest hardness and thermal conductivity. These properties are utilized in major industrial applications such as cutting and polishing tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, Diamonds for jewelry requires a diamond Certification. Labs like GIA, AGS, IGI, EGL, GSI, and HRD provide a certificate which describes diamond and its characteristics. Color, Clarity, length and width is scrutinized by the professionals under the microscope. A diamond’s 4C’s represent the four main components of its beauty and structure: Cut, Color, Clarity and Carat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From deep blues to the stunning red, diamonds are sparkling crystals which are a sign of royalism and capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Diamonds/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Diamonds/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 048, Deep Generative Modeling of LiDAR Data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the summary of the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.01180&quot;&gt;Deep Generative Modeling of LiDAR Data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper covers the niche problem of generative modeling on lidar scans. Often, the data through the sensor is corrupted or has some inconsistencies. This might lead to a tumultuous behaviour within the robot thus affecting the output. To address this problem, developing an intelligent system is an important mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative modeling has shown massive growth in images but it is still in its toddler stages compared to 3D and lidar data. Thus, the authors have devised to project the 3D lidar sensory data to a 2D grid. The spherical lidar data is converted to a 2D grid through a two-step process. Step 1, the N (x,y,z) points are clustered into H parts on the basis of the angle of elevation. Points with the same angle of elevation buckets into the same cluster. In the next step, the 360 degree plane is divided into W parts. This gives us a grid of H x W. Information of each cell is accumulated into a tensor of size 3 — H x W x 3. This data can be easily converted to the polar coordinate system. The devised technique is used on the KITTI dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the data is prepared, the baselines are developed on AtlasNet using the KITTI data without any preprocessing. Paper talks about conditional and unconditional generation. In conditional generation the data is slightly tampered with some noise, here Gaussian Noise, and then remodeled to reconstruct the input intelligently. Since the modeling is not based on sampling but instead on reconstruction, VAE and AE are used. Simultaneously, for unconditional generation, GANs are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rigorous evaluation criteria for generative modeling is still an open problem. But here the authors have used the Earth Mover metric — optimal transport problem —  and Chamfer distance. Moreso, for training parameters they have randomly selected learning rate, latent dimensions and batch size and experimented with 10 different configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed adversarial network can produce highly realistic images. Also VAE for lidar data provides a very robust solution to deal with noisy data.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Lidar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Lidar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 047, Avatar : The Last Airbender</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I started to watch Avatar : The Last Airbender, when Netflix &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/netflix/status/1261419683116249089?lang=en&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; about it in May. Like any other series, I followed it at snail’s pace but without striking my  attention I endlessly binged all three seasons. It is an animated adventure series which was originally aired for three seasons on Nickelodeon during 2005-2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar: The Last Airbender takes place in a fantasy world set up in Eastern Culture. The undertones of the series follow the Ancient Chinese philosophy of Yin and Yang. Human civilization is divided into four nations : Air, Water, Earth and Fire. Each nation has its natural element, on the basis of its society, and within each nation exist people known as “benders” who have the innate power to play and the ability to control and manipulate elements of their nation. The show’s creator has assigned each bending style its own martial art form. This world is menaced by Fire Nation, who attacks and exploits every other nation and land to form a totalitarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar can restore balance to nature, who in correspondence of the story is reborn as a different member of the four nations. During its lifetime, Avatar has to master the prowess of all the four elements. In this series, Avatar is a 12 year old monk named Aang, who was born to two Air Nomads. Shortly before the 100 years of war, Aang froze in an iceberg for hundred years. He emerged, still biologically 12 years old, into the world engulfed by war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aang teams up with two members of the southern water tribe — Katara, the waterbender and Sokka. They travel the world in the search of masters of elements to end the war. Paralleling this, Zuko, abandoned prince of Fire nation aimed to defeat and capture Avatar and restore his pride. Meanwhile, Aang meets secondary characters who helped him master all the elements to bring back harmony to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aang and his friends along with his six-legged flying bison practiced martial arts and went on expeditions. The world of the show is full of fanciful places — A jungle denser than amazon, rocky terrain, upside-down temples carved under cliffs, a vast desert with a library of limitless knowledge, and even an island on the back of a beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar managed to embrace all the movements taught by the masters while still following his cultural appropriation. Being a monk he has never killed any living being. As Sozin’s Comet approaches Earth, the fire nation fledged to full power and aimed to capture the world. Worried he might have to kill Firelord, Aang meditated into Avatar State to gain knowledge of all the past Avatars. Confused by the wisdom but determined by his principles, Aang refuses to kill Firelord Ozai. Aang used elemental bending to take away Ozai’s firebending power, removing his ability to wage war. This marked the end of the war. During the coronation, Prince Zuko, who fought for purity promised to aid the world in the postwar reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar the last airbender is full of small acts of kindness. It paints the value of hope and empathy while in the world which is full of terrible things — war, imperialism, genocide. Although the world does not face a threat as clear as fire nation, that doesn’t mean that there aren’t issues that are meant to be addressed — climate change, corruption, political divides. Aang and his friends have shown us that despite the scale of our world’s issue, we all play a role in solving them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Avatar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Avatar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 046, Pandemic and Exams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Exam and Election season in India are amazing. These two seasons cause more deaths and devastation than any other, especially the former one. Thank You Indian society for making students feel bad about themselves. Thank You for forcing them to commit suicide. Thank You for forcing them to break their mental peace. Thank You for making them feel horrible. Aha! Let’s add a topping on it, exams during a pandemic. It was fine until the assignments but exams amidst this pandemic are going to be a hodgepodge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of exams is to test students what they are taught. It gives you the ability to stay focused under pressure. It brushes your skill. I believe it does but being locked in the house for more than 100 days doesn’t make the situation better despite it makes it worse. When the lockdown was imposed I planned to take on cutting things off my bucket list. I am sure all you must have thought that way but slowly the stress, anxiety, fear, pressure started to build up. Everyone is on the verge of mental breakdown. The surrounding is depressed. The world is depressed. The world is becoming hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we taking exams? Are we even taught anything? Irregular classes, poor internet, irritated students and teachers — the feudal system. The world is going down, the economy is crashing, protests are being held, police brutality is peaking and most importantly, people are dying because of COVID-19. People are scared. Even the calmest of the minds are flipping out. What do you expect from young adults? Their prefrontal cortex is not developed. This compromises to rageful decisions, sloppy behaviour, recklessness, impulsive nature and disturbed brain. These are the future of the nation. While they are gradually slipping into the cruel world, it’s hard for them to understand the nature of people, making them anxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions of UGC has contributed more to this. Students who are already under pressure are being provided with confusing statements. Authorities have constantly changed their decision in the nick of time. State governments suggested not to hold examinations then UGC, on July 6, issued a notice to conduct examinations of the terminal semester and final year, suggesting to hold exams by September 30. While WHO has passed guidelines suggesting that the worst is yet to come. UGC believes all of it will settle by September 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities have tried mock examinations but thanks to the poor internet infrastructure, the system has been brutally compromised. There is a case of a girl committing suicide because her father couldn’t afford a smartphone for her class. Government is slowly transforming schools and colleges to COVID centers and at the same time asking students to take offline exams. Believe it or not, things are getting out of hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative is to cancel final semester exams while using the average of marks obtained in previous semesters as a proxy of final semester marks. This will meet the guidelines of pandemic and there is nothing to worry about the connectivity because prior examination results are already available. 
While we talked about mental health when Sushant Singh Rajput died, at the same time UGC has forced exams and increased the mental tension of the final year students. Aren’t those officers aware of the fragile and panicky age of young adults, or officers at UGC love the cheap and reliable idea of exams for creating hierarchy in society?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Exams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Exams/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 045, Game of Life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1970, John Conway published an eclectic paper about cellular automata — the game of life. It is a simulation that chooses how a complex thing like mind can come from a basic set of rules. This simulation consists of a grid, like a chessboard, extending infinitely in all directions. Each lid of the grid can either be lit up or dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cellular Automata&lt;/strong&gt; is a collection of colored cells in a grid like pattern to represent the state of that machine or program. It evolves over time according to the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game of Life is a zero player game, whose evolution depends on the initial stage of the game. Defined on 8 adjacent grid cells, the configuration of the next state depends on the configuration of the given cell and its corresponding neighbour cells. At each step in the time, following transitions can take place:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a cell is alive then it stays alive if it has either 2 or 3 live neighbours.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the cell is dead then it springs to life only in the case that it has 3 live neighbours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial patterns constitute the seed of the system. This elementary cellular automata either blooms out or dies off. It is not necessary the structure becomes complex and intriguing nor is it necessary it must die off, there is a possibility that the structure oscillates and repeats itself every few moves. Block, beehive, loaf, boat — remain static and never change; blinker, toad, beacon oscillates, while glider and lightweight spaceship changes configuration over configuration and repeats the initial seed at different locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_static.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt; --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_oscillate.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt; --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_repeat.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behaviour of plants and animals can be better understood by these simple rules. Behaviour that seems intelligent, such as ant colonies might just be simple rules that we don’t understand yet. Traffic problems might be solved by analyzing them with the mathematical tool and breaking it down to fundamental. Computer viruses are also examples of cellular automata. Finding the pattern in these viruses might also be hidden in this life. Human diseases can be cured if we could better understand how cells live and die. Exploring the galaxies could be easier if the machines could be invented that could create a replica of themselves. Game of life helps in understanding all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conway’s game of life is an existential proof that complex and unpredictable nature is possible due to a simple but recursive system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Images from &lt;a href=&quot;https://natureofcode.com/book/chapter-7-cellular-automata/&quot;&gt;Chapter 7: The Nature of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Game-of-life/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Game-of-life/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 044, Sugar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A carbohydrate used to address your loved one because of its sweetness. But sugar is not good for your body, not your loved ones — or maybe but the carbohydrate. Sugar is bitter to you and your body. It has a drug like effect at the center of the brain. Sweet food — just like salty and fatty food — can produce addiction-like effects in the human brain. It makes you lose self-control, drives your anxiety and oftentimes triggers your overeating habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early humans when the food was scarce, sugar acted like a high-calorie food. But now when the food is abundant, it contributes to obesity and diabetes. Overeating alters the brain reward system which in turn drives overeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glucose, Fructose, Sucrose, Maltose, Lactose, Dextrose, Starch are all types of sugar. Check the labels on your food items. Sugar isn’t just in candies and dessert, it’s also added to tomato sauce, yogurt, flavoured water etc. Since sugar is everywhere it’s important to understand how it affects the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever Since it is found everywhere, chances are you are overdoing it. In excess, it negatively affects your body and brain. Eating sugar rewards your brain — dopamine release reward. Whole food doesn’t release as much dopamine as sugar does. Dopamine gives you the feeling of pleasure. Once you get used to it, dopamine regulates your moods. As soon as you eat sugar your blood pressure rises and gives you a quick burst of energy. But as it starts to break and get absorbed in the body you start to get jittery and anxious. In turn, you eat more sugar and this makes the situation worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive sugar causes tooth decay, causes inflammation on the skin and makes skin age faster. The extra insulin in your bloodstream can make walls of arteries grow thicker which in turn gets stiffer, stressing the heart. This passive damage causes heart diseases like heart attack, stroke, heart failure etc. Similarly, Pancreas get overworked while pumping out more and more insulin. Too much sugar can lead to kidney failure. One who consumes more sugar weighs more and we are aware of the downsides of obesity. Each of these exploits your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, think about all the different kinds of sugar. Each one is unique but each one causes a dopamine trigger making it more addictive. In this way, excessive sugar acts like a drug.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
