<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 20:54:49 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 20:54:49 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 014, Cult of Q</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2020/06/qanon-nothing-can-stop-what-is-coming/610567/&quot;&gt;The Prophecies of Q&lt;/a&gt;, cover story of The Atlantic, June 2020 edition, by &lt;b&gt;Adrienne LaFrance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reddit, 4chan, 8chan: these anonymous platforms, are home to numerous conspiracy theories about untouchable and secretive cabal. One of which is QAnon conspiracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QAnon started as fringe theory online, which believes that the world, especially the US is controlled by a powerful organization called Deep States. According to Q mythology, President Donald Trump was elected by the support of highest military intelligence in this time to deal with the great upheaval. The main idea is that Q society and Trump are fighting Satanic Deep States which includes Hillary Clinton, the Obamas, the Bushes and other elites. These Satanic elites are believed to be sex traffickers who torture children and drink adrenochrome for their magical powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea originated in October 2016, when Wikileaks publicly released the emails stolen from the account of John Podesta, a former White House chief of staff and chair of Hillary Clinton’s 2016 U.S. presidential campaign. The emails repeatedly mentioned Comet. These emails were mostly about fundraising but some high profile Trump supporters claimed, on 4chan which later spread to more accessible social media platforms, that these emails are evidence of ritualistic child abuse. This created chaos. Edgar Maddison Welch, on December 4, 2016 arrived at Comet Ping Pong in order to self-investigate the theory — “Pizzagate”. Earlier, these theories were posted by anonymous users, but in October 2017 an anonymous user with username “Q” who claimed to be a government insider posted about the arrest of Hillary Clinton on 4chan, which evidently did not happen. Q wanted to make people believe it is a military official with Q level clearance or a classified intelligence officer. Slowly Q started dropping intel, often incomprehensible, filled with abbreviation, cryptic reference and jargons. QAnon, the followers of Q used these hints to try and decipher the secret that Q was trying to pass. These posts were based on a history of false, baseless and unsubstantiated claims which led to wrong prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bring order to the chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultish devotion of QAnon in the times of pandemic has developed the most dangerous conspiracy theory about the COVID-19. The group thought that the pandemic was something to celebrate cover for the secret arrest of the Deep State elites by Trump’s administration. Up until March 23, when Q posted a theory that coronavirus was developed with the joint venture of China and democrats to stop Trump’s reelection by destroying the economy. In other instances, QAnon launched #FilmYourHospital to charge into the hospital and look for sick patients and cars in the garage to uncover the tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FBI claimed these conspiracy theories by QAnon are “potential domestic terrorism threat”. Infodemic should be regulated and controlled otherwise it would be a threat to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. I wonder if there is a similar group in India.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cult-of-Q/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cult-of-Q/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 013, Birdie Study</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1989, Japan’s Shinkansen Bullet Trains were tendered to go faster but they had a problem. They were fast but every time it exited a tunnel — it was loud. The noise was coming from a variety of sources. Whenever a train sped through the tunnel it compressed the air and pushed it through the other end creating a sonic boom. These deafening waves could be heard uptil 400 meters. An engineering team was set up to design quieter, faster and more efficient trains. Eiji Nakatsu, General Manager of the Technical Development Department, also a birdwatcher, led the team to redesign trains based on the aerodynamics of 3 birds — Owl, Penguin and Kingfisher. Nakatsu remodeled the pantograph by getting inspired from the owl’s feathers, reducing noise by using the same curvatures and indents. The Adelie Penguin whose body allows them to swim and slide effortlessly helped in restructuring the shaft of the pantograph. And most notable of all, the kingfisher’s beak inspired the train nose model. When the redesigned train was first run, it was 10% faster, used 15% less electricity and stayed under 70 dB noise limit in residential areas. Birds, the world’s best engineers, teaches us a lot about avian efficiency and redesigning principles of aircrafts and other technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;V-shaped Flying pattern&lt;/strong&gt;
There is a good reason some birds fly in a V. As birds flap, it creates a vortex of air which creates lift for trailing birds. Which means the bird can fly longer without getting tired. This is often considered as surfing, inspiring engineers to develop strategies to conserve fuel in aircrafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bird Head Stabilization&lt;/strong&gt;
With a large number of vertebrae and muscles in their neck, birds can hold their head in a position even when their body is moving. This helps birds to focus on the predator and maneuver through complex terrains. By keeping their head stable, birds don’t have to rely alone on their eyes for image stabilization. Although Gaze Stabilization is complex and poorly understood, it has inspired modern steadicam technologies — Gimbal, Camera Stabilizer. As we will understand more about stabilization, we can develop better models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Woodpecker and Shock Absorption&lt;/strong&gt;
Woodpeckers spiral through the tree trunks in search of insects. They peck at upto 20 times per second and create a force almost 10 times greater than what would cause concussion to humans. How do they do it? Scientists have discovered that a certain portion of their skull is soft and shock absorbent, which allows them to bear the energy they produce. Researchers are set out to develop artificial analogues to build mechanical shock absorbing systems to protect microelectronics. Also, these shock absorbing systems can protect spacecraft from the damage of collisions with small meteorites and space debris. Furthermore, sports equipment with shock absorbent property would be of incredible use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the lightweight interlaced mesh of feathers which have enabled birds to conquer gravity and take air in an extraordinary way; energy efficient Eagle’s Talon to pluck the prey, hovering technique of Hummingbird etc will help us develop and optimize technologies by biomimicking birds. Birdwatching can lead us to achieve modern marvels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Birdie-Study/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Birdie-Study/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 012, Cave Painting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Chauvet-Pont-d’Arc Caves, in Southeast France, are one of the most important prehistoric sites ever discovered. Although these artworks were designed 35000 years ago but the animals drawn on the cave are considered to be masterpieces.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cavePainting.jpg&quot; height=&quot;80%&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Rhinoceros Alcove in Chauvet-Pont-d’Arc Cave, France&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cave art depicting groups of rhinos, humans hunting boar and buffaloes, human-animal hybrid etc are nearly 44,000 years old, making it one of the earliest known cave paintings by humans. Cave Paintings are pictorial records of storytelling and figurative art. The seeds of artistic creativity were sown as early as 65,000 years ago by Neanderthals (subspecies of Archaic Human) in Spain. It flourished in Europe where it burst and came into full fledged view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most common subjects of these cave doodles were wild animals — bison, horses, auroch, deer, human figures and symbolic art. They were developed using organic and inorganic pigments — red and yellow ochre, hematite, manganese oxide, charcoal etc. To further accentuate the features of the animals, artists used natural contours of the walls. These symbolic and religious paintings are believed to be drawn by Shamans, who went deep inside the cave to perform ceremonial trance and drew their spirit animals. 
These faded yet stark and evocative designs tell us about the distant past and provide us with the evidence of time. More precisely, it tells us about human evolution. Cave Painters weren’t just Picasso, drawing impressions on the walls. Rather, they had  high-level cognitive processing to develop a communication system. Moreover, these cave graffiti tells us about the features of animals of that time, extinct animals and animals who have emerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The motivation that drove cave artists might be a mystery but the treasure it possesses to the contemporary world is immense.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cave-Painting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cave-Painting/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 011, Today: A Lazy Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After my &lt;a href=&quot;https://square-1111.github.io/2020/Battle-of-laziest/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; on laziness, I decided to take a day off, Because - Why not? And believe me, it was a great day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 10 o’clock in the morning when I snoozed my alarm for the last time, not because I didn’t want to sleep more but ma had different plans. She loves me so much that she came with a rolling pin (belan). I got overwhelmed by her love and woke up. I was about to step down from the bed, a thought popped “Today is a lazy day, Why don’t you stew in your filth for some more time” and it was a life changing decision. Lazily I picked up my phone and scrolled the devils plunger — Reddit for an hour. Bored! I slept for another hour. Waking up, I gathered some strength to get my laptop which was 3 ft away resting on the table. I consumed some of the weirdest content on YouTube. Finally, I decided to leave the bed after receiving Google Classroom’s notification. Assignment! Uh Huh, I also second it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my chores, I decided to write my assignment. Wait a minute! Were there any tasks on schedule? Caught me! Nah there weren’t any. I had zero idea about the subject, but who needs it when I have gracious friends around me. With every page I wrote I wandered something bizarre — What if our eyes popped out from the socket abruptly? More ideas provoked as I finished the assignment. Next, I performed the dark art of fat loss and right after it, I had 3 rasgullas. Those rasgullas made me so sleepy that I dozed off for some more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing I remember - I woke up for dinner and this made my mom think that I had smoked weed. While watching another episode of FRIENDS for the gazillionth time, I had dinner. Film rolled and I binged episode after episode of FRIENDS. &lt;strong&gt;11:30 PM&lt;/strong&gt; and I had not yet decided what to write about. That’s when my friend suggested writing about today. Finally, after such a tiring day, I gathered all my courage to post this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one really happy day but I might go insane if I follow it more often. Now, if you will please let me snore again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good Bye. Peace out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Lazy-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Lazy-day/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 010, Battle of Laziest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sloth vs Koala — These two might make you super sleepy. Don’t take out your pillows just yet. Instead, grab a coffee. Don’t worry, you ain’t gonna miss anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sloths are low energy loafers, inhabitant to Central and South America. These are drowsy tree-dwellers who sleep 15 hours a day and barely move even when awake. They are so snail-paced that they grow algae on their skin, it makes them less noticeable to predators. If you groom Sloths, thousands of moths might fly out. In fact, when they groom themselves, they move their fingers so slow that the moths have no difficulty keeping up with the pace. Once every week, they come down to defecate and cover their poop with leaves. While on ground, they move slowly by digging their front claws into the dirt and dragging their bodies. Despite the fact that they don’t do much, sloth has a constant smile on the face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next contestant is Koala. Often known as Koala-bear, it is barely related to the bear family, instead Koala belongs to Marsupials family. These sleepy-headed creatures doze off for 18 hrs a day. Found in Australia, these convenient eaters hardly leave the Eucalyptus tree where they get endless supply of their favorite food — Eucalyptus leaves. This means less time searching for food  and more time for snoring. Koalas might not be the smartest animal but they are cute, cuddly and extremely photogenic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does it mean laziness contributes to happiness? :p&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these beings are either sleeping or daydreaming. But who is the winner? Umm, None. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/proishan11&quot;&gt;Ishan Singh&lt;/a&gt;, a friend of mine with a weird hairdo. He has achieved new heights of laziness in this lockdown. He hasn’t left the sofa in a while and has developed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lissencephaly&quot;&gt;smooth brain&lt;/a&gt;. Reaching this new feat of idleness, sloth and koala are no competition to him. As a matter of fact, he has moved beyond the illusions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, get back to your fast paced schedules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. Sadly, earlier this year many Koalas were killed because of Australian Fire.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PS2. Thank You &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/proishan11&quot;&gt;Ishan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Battle-of-laziest/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Battle-of-laziest/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 009, Dark Matter and Dark Energy : the holding forces</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever Since the Big Bang, our Universe is expanding and reaching new feat. If gravity was playing its role, the universe would have collapsed. Also, gravity cannot explain the high rotation speed of the galaxies. Either the gravity behaves in an odd fashion or there might be some matter in the Universe that holds everything together while the Universe is expanding. Indeed there exists a substance termed as Dark Matter. Dark matter is the most mysterious yet ubiquitous substance in the Universe. Our Universe has around 68% dark energy, 37% Dark Matter. The rest 5% is everything on Earth, everything ever observed by instruments and all normal material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I feel so tiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 5 basic elements — Space, Air, Fire, Water, and Earth — of the material world, Dark Matter could not be seen, felt, smelt or tasted. In fact, It does not even interact with electromagnetic waves. This means it does not absorb, reflect or emit light, making it more difficult to spot. Researchers have seen some potential interaction with gravitational forces. What is it? As of now, we know more about what it isn’t than what it is. Dark Matter isn’t anti matter, otherwise it would have produced gamma rays when annihilated with normal matter. Neither is it a black hole, or failed stars or clouds of gas or anything else that can be made from normal matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations are trying to figure out its presence to understand more about the Universe. Scientists have installed sensitive sensors under the Earth to see if Dark Matter interacts with classical elements. Similarly, Satellites, through a special Gamma Ray Telescope, traces the energy imprints of dark matter collision. Moreover, at CERN, researches are smashing normal particles together inside the Large Hadron Collider just to check if there is subsequent change in the property of the material inside. Although the results aren’t successful, we understand more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several theories explaining dark matter. Albert Einstein first explained it as the property of the space, suggesting empty space is not nothing. Later, in one version of Einstein’s gravity theory, he proposed a cosmological constant. Through cosmological constant, he predicted that “empty space” can possess its own energy and would not be diluted. As more space comes, more energy will be generated. This defines the ever expanding nature of the Universe. No one actually understood why cosmological constant is even there. Another theory, derived from Quantum theory of matter, proposed that empty space is made of virtual particles that continually form and disappear. But using this theory, when the energy of dark matter was calculated, it was wrong by an order of 10&lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;. There are other incomplete theories which, at the end, lead to nothing. So, the mystery remains unrevealed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark Matter is a mystery that we want to understand. Demystifying it would be a key to a whole new understanding of physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dark Matter matters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Dark-Matter-and-Dark-energy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Dark-Matter-and-Dark-energy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 008, Being One</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Don’t overthink, there is nothing whimsical, scary, poetic, it’s just a post about number one. No no no, not about number one but about NUMBER 1. Ugh! It’s just too hard. Nevermind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One is the loneliest number” is not just a song but a truth in the world of Mathematics. 1 is no fun to play with. Multiplying and dividing by one is so underwhelming. Mathematically, it is called “unity” and it has even more strange properties — the square root of one is one. With all this unlikeliness, one wasn’t even considered as a number for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle, Euclid and many of the founding fathers of Mathematics did not consider one as a number. Why? They reasoned that the number is “multitude composed of units”. Under this definition, one is not a number but the seed for a number. And I used to feel I am a sufferer of FOMO. But this isn’t the end. In Contemporary world, when one is considered as a number there are other hustles. Historically, One has been on and off the hook of prime numbers list. With all the properties of being a prime, mathematicians suggested one does not preserve the uniqueness of the factorization. Finally, The fundamental theorem of arithmetic which states that “Every positive integer can be represented as the product of prime numbers.” suggested the world of mathematics to exclude one from the definition of prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[6 = 2\times 3\]
\[6 = 3\times 2\]
\[6 = 1\times 2 \times 3\]
\[6 = 1\times 1\times 2 \times 3\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two are unique factorization but latter two aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;One is the loneliest number you will ever do.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might be the loneliest number but one was never the loser. It has overpowered the world of technology along with zero —  binary notation. No number can be formed without the approval of one. In Grandi’s series when one was added and subtracted infinitely to add up to \(\frac{1}{2}\), made one quite confused about its existence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[S = 1-1+1-1+1-1+…\]
\[1-S = 1 - (1-1+1-1…..) = S\]
\[1-S = S\]
\[S = \frac{1}{2}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One” might as well have its own problems, but it is ruling the world with peace. Next time you feel low or anxious or sad, think about the struggles of one — From not even getting considered as a number to being one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Being-One/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Being-One/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 007, Cyberbullying</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Bullying is someone using their power to hurt someone physically, mentally or socially, it is much more worse than being mean. But with technologies in hand you don’t need to be powerful to harass anyone — And I present to you Cyberbullying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, there are various ways of cyberbullying, sending, posting or sharing negative, wrong information about anyone. These depraved activities to harass or defame someone makes the victim angry, sad, anxious, depressed and oftentimes suicidal which takes toll upon their mental health over years. Mostly, teenagers are either victims or perpetrators of cyberbullying. Their developing prefrontal cortex — a part of the brain which helps in making decisions and controlling impulses — often provokes them to take stupid decisions when poked even slightly. Ever Since we are in the middle of the pandemic, Gen Z’s are spending more time scrolling Instagram, Facebook, Snapchat for personal or educational purposes, internet hate has increased and so has cyberbullying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could happen anytime, anywhere leaving the victim with no place to feel safe. Victims are tormented by the hate they get through messages or through the hate page solely dedicated to trashing a person. Yes, you read it correct, purposely built HATE PAGES. With the anonymity features of social media platforms the picture has become scarier, the sufferers do not know who is organizing the attacks. Presence of these toxicities makes me feel queasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberbullying is more pernicious when it comes to children who do not have the resilience to deal hatred like an adult. Just because it takes place over the internet and does not have physical threat parents generally ignore it. This leaves the victim in a timid spot. This is why 9 out of 10 of the cyberbullied do not tell their guardians about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media platforms are trying to curb floods of toxic, extreme content and misinformation. Instagram, which has the most number of young audiences, is using machine learning algorithms to detect cyberbullying in photos and captions. Parents should start to talk to their kids about cyberbullying. Products like “&lt;a href=&quot;www.rethinkwords.com&quot;&gt;ReThink&lt;/a&gt;” are developing solutions to stop cyberbullying before the damage is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Research shows that when adolescents are alerted to rethink their decision, they change their minds 93% of the time. Using ReThink™, the overall willingness of an adolescent to post an offensive message reduced from 71% to 4%.&lt;br /&gt;
— Trisha Prabhu, Inventer ReThink&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberbullying is as heinous a crime. Awareness is the key to prevent from getting harassed online. Children should be made aware about the consequences of sharing personal information on the internet. It cannot be stopped until everyone takes responsibility to report any of such behaviour.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;”Stop ignoring cyberbullying. Let’s make internet a better place!”&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cyberbullying/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cyberbullying/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 006, Clickbaits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before starting this post, I watched a video on “Advertisements vs Reality” not for research purpose but *CLICKBAIT* — you will be happy to know I have achieved enlightenment. If I could have achieved enlightenment by clicking on the clickbaits, I would be a genius today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These catchy headlines are all over the place — news articles, Youtube, social media posts. Clickbaits have infiltrated the internet and have made the internet frustrating. The science of virality, clickbait, is analogous to alchemy that turns lead to gold. Clickbaits play along with our emotions, providing us comfort. But clickbaits are not just in your head — digital marketers, writers, editors play a role all along to understand the behavioural sciences of humans. These folks have mastered the skills to produce compelling clickbaits to grab your attention. While you might feel sadness, anger and fear, you still somehow click on the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pleasure of dopamine high keeps us motivated to constantly be aroused by clickbaits and fall into the pitfall, following links repeatedly. Through every compelling clickbait we click we activate a pathway for dopamine. Dopamine is released and creates an itch that can be fed by the promised clickbait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clickbait, noun: Things I don’t like on the Internet.
— Joshua Benton, Nieman Journalism lab at Harvard University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have you opened Youtube just to watch a single video but ended up watching more? The reason is clickbaits, it is taking your time as well as mental resources without your knowledge. Social media feeds are full of over-promising headlines. Once you start to ingest articles/videos you anticipate that you are learning something. Ever wondered how credible these clickbaits are? The studies in these articles often limit many factors like geographic location, age, gender. Thus they cannot provide a generalized truth. To mitigate this issue consumers should take a look at the case study on which the article is reporting on and read many studies. But this task of digging the truth is often not so appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the internet is that everyone wants your attention. And as long as there are clickbaits people will continue to click on it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Clickbaits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Clickbaits/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 005, Sneakers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Air Jordan, Yeezys, PUMA Suede, Converse, Vans — Ring a bell? Sneakers. Australians call them “runners”. The British know them as “trainers” and Americans address them as “tennis shoes” or “sneakers’. Whatever you call them, these rubber-soled, casual shoes are worn by billions of people around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago Sneakers were considered ungentlemanly and were part of alternative society, but now it has totally taken over the fashion industry. Sneakers are considered art. These youth-cultured streetwears are worn on runways, red carpets, workplaces and where not. Sneakers are versatile staples which go with everything. This is partly because of the evolution in our professional lives. There are barely any jobs which require the employee to be suited and booted. Engineers, journalists, teachers, stylists etc are far more likely to wear sneakers than a pair of heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the glamour associated with sneakers, people are obsessed about them. There are sneakerheads with a collection of more than 1000 pairs of sneakers. Sneaker collection is a real thing. Have you seen people queue to buy the latest iPhone — sneakerheads camp outside the sneaker store for days before the sale, and these sales happen way more often. More interestingly, a few minutes after the sale, thousands of these pairs are on eBay for two or three times the retail price. The global sneaker market was valued at 70.1 billion USD in 2018 and is expected to be 108 billion USD by the end of 2025. This craziness is so intense that people have created their own sneaker portfolios to manage their sneaker prices. Is this addiction more like drugs or stocks? Sneakers are a legal and accessible investment opportunity. Sneakers have their own democratized, yet unregulated, stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To meet these crazy demands, companies have to increase the production. But making shoes has become more complicated, more labor intensive and in some ways more dangerous. The heel insole, midsole and upper layer are made up of synthetic textiles. Mining the fossil fuels to develop the textiles generates tons of greenhouse gas and uses lots of energy. The outer sole is made of synthetic blend of natural rubber. Next, sneakers are composed of several discrete parts which are manufactured at different locations to make it cheap. But the transportation of these parts to the assembly line emits even more carcinogenic gases. Once all components arrive at the assembly line they are cut, melted, baked, cooled, glued and then stitched which accounts for the more carbon footprint. Ever Since all the parts are glued so tightly that it is almost impossible to recycle them. Either they are burnt or left in landfills where it takes them thousands of years to degrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, sneakers are rendered as art and have a cult status. But we need to balance our love for sneakers with sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sneakers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sneakers/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
