<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 13:12:00 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 13:12:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 039, Sponge City</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The entire world is filled with concrete. Natural water system is disregarded. In the meantime,  extreme weather conditions — floods, droughts — are frequent because of climate change. China has been hard hit by this. To solve this problem, they came up with the idea of Sponge City in 2015. No no, it isn’t the place where Spongebob Squarepants lives. Instead, it is a city structured to absorb and capture rainwater. It helps in flood prevention. It is a sustainable, regenerative, eco-friendly, low-impact, future-proofed, zero-carbon solution for the drainage system at urban scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before explaining more about what Sponge City actually is, let us first understand what issues does Sponge City intends to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water Scarcity in urban and semi-urban areas —&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the time we get water from aquifers underneath us. The rainwater is absorbed by the ground and is filtered through. This water reflourishes the aquifers. With extreme urbanization and impermeable concrete structures, the aquifers cannot restore to their levels. Thus less water is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polluted water discharged into the rivers and seas —&lt;/strong&gt; Now that water cannot be absorbed, it gets drained into sewage. This mixture is more polluted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Degradation of urban ecosystem and increase in the intensity of flooding —&lt;/strong&gt; Because of urbanization and industrialization there is a drastic change in the climatic conditions. This leads to extreme weather conditions. Flooding leads to water clogging and disturbances in the natural water cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deal with these problems, the idea of Sponge City has surfaced. The idea of Sponge City is to create a pervious system to allow the flow of water. The water is absorbed in the sponge-like environment and is stored in urban aquifers which can be used by the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sponge city needs to be abundant with space that allows water to seep through it. Besides the permeable asphalt and water-absorbing materials, a sponge city requires contiguous open green spaces, interconnected channels and ponds that can naturally store and filter water. Green roofs can retain and filter water before releasing it into ground. More importantly, moderating the usage of water is very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sponge city provides a wide range of advantages. More clean water, Cleaner groundwater, reduction in flood risks, greener and healthier environment. Inspired by this model, lately, many countries are studying and trying to incorporate this system into their environment.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sponge-City/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sponge-City/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 038, Minimalism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What comes into your mind when you think of minimalism? A perfectly lit white room with no material or extremely simple artwork. That’s how the concept of minimalism is portrayed. But when it comes to living a minimalist life, living in a well lighted room without any material would be quite morbid and deprecating. Some people follow this extreme form of minimalism; it’s not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism is not about removing everything but it’s about decluttering in order to achieve happiness, peace and sanctity. Consider an example: A person wants a cup of coffee after waking up to feel alive or happy. They start to think this is what makes them happy. But slowly this requirement locks them in. They start to structure their life around it. For a lot of us, it’s evening tea or the Internet for entertainment and news or the need to watch TV in the evening to unwind time. There is nothing wrong with it. But gradually these things which make us happy start to pile up and control our life. What happens if you let go of these things and keep it as a “nice-to-have” option? It might make you feel sad for a while but it will free you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism is intentionally living with things you really need — those items that support the purpose. Removing all the distractions of excess possessions to focus more on things that matter. Living a minimalist lifestyle reduces your stress and anxiety, improves your sleep, helps in clarity of thoughts, boosts your productivity and creativity and importantly helps you to save money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you start to declutter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are new, start with 5 minutes a day to build momentum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put everything in one pile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask yourself: do you really need this? Do you use it regularly? Do you love it? If the answer to any of these is no, then recycle, donate, or give it to someone who might want it. Put it in a box for these purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to do more than 5 minutes a day, go ahead but be careful not to overdo it in the beginning or you will think it’s difficult to continue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical decluttering is just one type, you should declutter your digital life as well. Declutter your calendar by prioritizing your commitments and saying no to non-essential things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a beautiful world of freedom and fresh breath hiding behind that clutter. Deciding how to declutter your home is up to you. A minimalist lifestyle teaches you how to say “No” to unsolicited things. This isn’t a prescription for how to live your life, but just something to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Minimalism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Minimalism/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 037, PS5</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Decepticons! The new flagship of Playstation is there. With high collar esque, Sony has unveiled PS5 — a console from an alien world.  Through the innumerous rumours, it’s been 7 years since PS4 was launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sony, on June 11, 2020, during the Sony PS5 reveal event showed off lots of games including Gran Turismo, Spider-Man : Miles Morales, Horizon 2: Forbidden West and many more. But the showstopper was the revelation  of the PS5 console itself. Sony uncovered two variants of PS5 which will be available at launch — PS5 and PS5 Digital Edition. The only difference between the two is that PS5 Digital Edition does not have Blu-ray drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS5 features a custom eight-core AMD Zen 2 CPU clocked at 3.5 GHz and a custom GPU  based on AMD’s RDNA 2 architecture hardware which promises 10.28 teraflops and 36 compute units clocked at 2.23GHz. To further improve the performance, Sony has replaced the HDD with an 825GB SSD and the 8 GB of DDR3 RAM of PS4 with 16 GB of GDDR6 RAM in PS5. The new PS5 provides a stunning gaming experience. Benchmarking Ray Tracing and super fast refresh rate of 120 Hz - the new iconic PS5 gives the user an exhilarating gaming experience. With an 8K Output support, Sony has truly created a futuristic machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sony, alongside PS5, introduced the DualSense game controller. It provides haptic feedback and adaptive triggers for an immersive gaming experience. The angle of hand trigger is also tweaked and the grip is provided to suffice ergonomics. The controller has an array of in-built microphone for in-game chat. To create epic gameplay, Sony has upgraded their Share button to Create button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As good as it may sound, PS5’s rival Xbox Series X is equally futuristic. With a custom processor of 12 teraflops, hardware accelerated ray tracing, variable rate shading Xbox might have a slight margin over PS5. Xbox has a black industrial design and vents on top with an underlying green sheet giving it a green halo which makes it look minimal yet modern. Compared to Xbox’s design, the rectangular design of PS5 has curves instead of edges. But PS5 has a very controversial design, the white plastic doesn’t have good respect in the techworld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bummer that they both did not reveal its price and release date but we can expect them in Holiday season 2020. I cannot wait to try them out. Oh poor boy! I cannot afford it. If you feel like gifting it, I won’t mind.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/PS5/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/PS5/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 036, Phi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh No! Not another greek alphabet. Do I have an obsession with them? Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/Pi/&quot;&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;, Phi is a symbolic representation of Golden Ratio. Golden Ratio, what? I have never heard of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find the &lt;strong&gt;Golden Ratio&lt;/strong&gt; when we divide the a line into two parts such that the ratio of the longer part to the shorter part is equal to the whole length divided by the shorter part.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GoldenRatio.png&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{a}{b} = \frac{a+b}{a}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic begins,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{a}{b} = 1 + \frac{a}{b}\]
\[\varphi = 1 + \frac{1}{\varphi}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention anything about recursion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = 1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{1 + \frac{1}{\ddots}}}}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevermind, let’s calculate its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(\varphi \)  is a solution of quadratic equation \(\varphi^2 - \varphi - 1 = 0\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\varphi = \frac{1+\sqrt{5}}{2} = 1.6180339887…\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another irrational number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the 1D line we can extend this in 2D. A 2D rectangle with side length \(a + b\) and \(a\). Following the properties of Golden Ratio, this rectangle is known as &lt;strong&gt;Golden Rectangle&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/goldenREc.png&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more to it. What if we subdivide the rectangle into a square and another rectangle and do it until we get two squares? Adding to it if we construct a spiral by pivoting at the corner of the square and turning it quarter in a continuous fashion, we will get &lt;strong&gt;Golden Spiral&lt;/strong&gt;. It is an ever-expanding spiral.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/spiralGolden.jpg&quot; height=&quot;40%&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s look from a different direction — bottom up. Consider two unit squares, combine them along the side. Attach a square of side length equal to the length of the larger side of the previously formed rectangle. We will get a similar pattern again. But if we look at the side length of squares we will find an engaging pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Length of the side of the next square is equal to the sum of the previous two. Remember &lt;strong&gt;Fibonacci Series&lt;/strong&gt;. When we take the ratio of two successive numbers from the Fibonacci Sequence then their value is very close to Golden Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B/A&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6667&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.625&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.615&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach towards infinity this ratio converges to the Golden Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough of mathematics Square. We understand, Golden Ratio has myriads of secrets. Why should we care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This divine proportion is all around us but its knowledge is confined to some mainstream recognition. Just like air — it’s there but we can’t see it. Similarly, Golden Ratio is omnipresent — from nature to music to architectural design. This tool is used by sculptors and artists to achieve remarkably accurate proportion and aesthetic compositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, we can find many instances of phi. The first guy was Luca Pacioli, a Franciscan friar who wrote a book called &lt;em&gt;De Divina Proportione&lt;/em&gt; back in 1509, which was named after the golden ratio. He did not tell about the aesthetics of Phi, instead the book focused on the Vitruvian System and its allegiance with golden ratio. Leonardo da Vinci was close friends with Pacioli. Da Vinci used this secret math in many of his famous paintings including Monalisa. Ancient Greek architecture used the Golden Ratio to determine pleasing dimensional relationships between the width of a building and its height, the size of the portico and even the position of the columns supporting the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phi is also said to be common in nature. Flower petals often come in Fibonacci numbers, such as five or eight, and pine cones grow their seeds outward in spirals of Fibonacci numbers. The ubiquitous nature of the Golden Ratio with its diverse and engaging application have made Phi another mathematical marvel.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Phi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Phi/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 035, Understanding Deep Learning Requires Rethinking Generalization</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a summary of Understanding Deep Learning Requires Rethinking Generalization paper which has been awarded for the best paper award at ICLR 2017. One of the best papers I have read so far, an eye-opener but quite verbose.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some models generalize better than others. But how do we distinguish between them? Answering this question would help us interpret the Artificial Neural Network (ANN) and help us create reliable and principled model architecture. Before we move further ahead, generalization error is the difference between training and testing error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central idea of the paper was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Deep neural networks easily fit random labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explicit regularization may improve generalization performance, but is neither necessary nor by itself sufficient for controlling generalization error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;randomization-test---fitting-random-labels-and-pixels&quot;&gt;Randomization Test  : Fitting Random Labels and Pixels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper explained the memorization capacity of the paper through randomizing labels and pixels. Authors trained several standard architectures with randomized labels. They found DNNs easily fit random labels. Moreso, the training error becomes zero, while the testing error is the same as any random chance. Furthering this they experimented with the pixels as well — shuffled pixels, random pixel, and gaussian noise. Surprisingly, stochastic gradient descent with unchanged hyperparameters can optimize weight to fit random labels perfectly. Adding to this astonishment, it was observed that as the noise in the image increases, the generalization error decreases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;explicit-regularization&quot;&gt;Explicit Regularization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explicit regularization techniques like dropout, weight decay, data augmentation are the tools of deep learning. These techniques were tested on random labels. As expected, the results were better. But the point that labels were shuffled makes it difficult to comprehend. Not only this  but implicit regularizers like early stopping also contributed for the betterment of the model trained on shuffled class labels. But we can’t miss that regularizers don’t tamper the weights too much but make subtle changes to make weights more smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all boils down to explain that deep neural networks work on rote memory than on semantic understanding, making neural networks far less interpretable and reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Understanding-Deep-Learning-Requires-Rethinking-Generalization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Understanding-Deep-Learning-Requires-Rethinking-Generalization/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 034, Is keeping animals in zoos cruel </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever Since our childhood, we have been taught that zookeepers are very cruel people and that they cage the animals inside bars. We are told that they miss the freedom to explore in nature. I agree. There are so many petitions to free the animals. People suggest animals exhibit neurotic behaviour when kept in captivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more to it. The art of getting animals used to the presence of humans is the science of zookeeping. Modern zoos are designed to give animals a high quality of life. The whole movement of zoos is more like colonialism. Animals get good quality food, proper flora, time to time health checkups and on top of that they are safe from all the threats, parasites, viruses they face in the jungle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a moment to realise what if we close the zoos and free all the animals. It would be similar to you being kicked out of the house and chased by people living on the streets. Do you think you will jump and dance with joy? No, you wouldn’t. Similarly, animals are territorial species, only a familiar territory would allow them to fulfil their needs of food and water. Finding all the places — lookouts, places for resting, eating, drinking etc — within the territory and getting food six days a week makes them super comfortable in the environment. Even the newly settled animals behave in the same way of owning the territory. There have been numerous cases where animals could flee but they didn’t because they are taken good care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But humans, they are the most dangerous animals in the zoo. We feed all kinds of foreign material to animals just to get entertained when it is clearly mentioned everywhere in zoos not to do so. Blades, nails, paperclip, pen, rubber band, comb, pieces of broken glass etc are the reason for the obituary of many animals in zoos as well outside. At zoos, cruelty is more active and direct. Animals get their arms broken, beaks cracked, digestive systems disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freeing the animals’ movement doesn’t seem so bad now. Instead, this will save the animals from the cruelty of the human world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When humans act with cruelty we characterize them as “animals”, yet the only animal that displays cruelty is humanity.”&lt;br /&gt;
— Anthony D. Williams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Zoo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Zoo/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 033, We need to be heard </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We all know what it feels like to be not heard. It doesn’t feel good, does it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our deepest longings — deeper than anything — is that other people should acknowledge our feelings. At peak moments we want our sufferings to be understood, anxieties to be noticed. It’s not that people want others to listen. To truly honour another person, we need to allow them to speak, without discouraging what people are saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The habit of not acknowledging others feelings stems from childhood. Parents, often the most loving ones, often stumble in this domain. It is not that they don’t intensely care about their kids but their love is quite different. They appreciate their child’s mood by ignoring it rather than subtly pushing the mood away or helping them out. Some of the conversations between parents and their child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Kid&lt;/ins&gt; : I feel sad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Parent&lt;/ins&gt; : You can’t be sad, we are on vacation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Kid&lt;/ins&gt; : I feel worried&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Parent&lt;/ins&gt; : Darling, it’s just ridiculous, there is nothing to be scared of&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Kid&lt;/ins&gt; : I wish there wasn’t any school ever ever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Parent&lt;/ins&gt; : Don’t be silly. You know we have to leave the house at 8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if such dialogues were slightly tweaked, for example, if the parents could say “It’s alright to be sad at the oddest of the times, even on this beach” or “I can see you are scared, the wind out there is really fierce” or “It must be horrible to do math after such a lovely weekend”? The child would grow to be a better adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why don’t we acknowledge the feelings? Fear. The feelings that we push away are emotionally inconvenient or troubling or upsetting. We love our friends and family so much, that we don’t want them to imagine that they might be sad, worried or lost. Furthermore, we think that acknowledging a difficult feeling might make it far worse than it actually is and won’t make them stronger. We fear that mirroring the emotions might make them feel worse. And the result of not getting heard is resentment and withdrawal. After a while, the effort to communicate is abandoned, which creates distance between relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we are missing is that most of us, once we’ve been heard we feel far better. The angry person gets less enraged once their frustration is recognized. Feelings become less brutal once they have been given a channel to propagate. We become bullies if no one listens to us, never because they listened to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful ways to enhance your relationship is to take time to sincerely listen to people with your heart. It might take some time and patience, but it is absolutely worth it. So next time someone is feeling bad don’t shush them with some ignorant reply, instead listen to them and be kind to them, who knows they might feel better.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/We-need-to-be-heard/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/We-need-to-be-heard/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 032, Legend of Lord Ganesha </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ganesha.jpg&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have grown up in a middle-class Hindu family, my pre-teen afternoons during summer vacations were spent learning multiplication tables, eating mangoes, playing Ludo and enjoying the myths in my mother’s lap — legends of Lord Ganesha, Goddess Parvati; stories from Ramayana and Mahabharat. I barely remember any of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Days aren’t the same, but today was different. Just like any other day in quarantine, I was on desk fiddling around with the laptop, mom was scrolling through her WhatsApp. It was not at all odd that she gets all kinds of audio forwards. But today it was, someone was narrating the myths of Lord Ganesha — an anecdote about why every Puja starts with Lord Ganesha’s name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long long ago, while Lord Vishnu and Goddess Lakshmi’s marriage, Lord Ganesha was left in-charge to guard Swargalok. He was tricked to do so because other deities were embarrassed of his physical appearance and his massive diet. The procession went on, when Narad Ji saw Lord Ganesha at the door of Swargalok and asked the reason. Withered Lord Ganesha told his sorrow to Narad Muni. On knowing this Narad suggested Lord Ganesha avenge his respect and devised a plan that would make deities realise Lord Ganesha’s importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Ganesha asked his Mushakraj to dig up the roads that lead to Goddess Lakshmi’s abode. Mushakraj followed the orders and bore the roads. As expected, the deities couldn’t proceed further, the wheels of their chariot got stuck in the earth. Everyone took their measures but the wheel did not move. No one could understand what was going around. A farmer, passing by, decided to help them. The farmer chanted Lord Ganesha’s name and pulled out the carriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmer, being asked by deities, explained that Lord Ganesha’s name has induced strength in him since he is the Remover of Obstacles. Deities realised that there is more to a being than his physical appearance, and they returned to apologize to Lord Ganesha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story tells us to Always stand up for your self-respect. I exchanged smiles, cut a mango and recalled those old days.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Legend-of-Lord-Ganesha/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Legend-of-Lord-Ganesha/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 031, Reinvent the wheel</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idiomatic Metaphor&lt;/strong&gt; : duplicate a basic method which has already previously been created or optimized by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask any sane person about the greatest discovery of all the time, they will agree that it’s the wheel. The wheel has been reinvented so many times that reinventing the wheel has now become an idiom. If it hadn’t been the plethora of inventors and engineers trying to improve and adapt wheels for various purposes, we would still be traveling in Fred Flintstone’s footmobile.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tenor.gif&quot; height=&quot;60%&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The materials we use have changed from stones to alloys to now carbon-based substances. The content of the wheel has changed, the rim, development of strokes, aerodynamics of the wheel all were possible because someone somewhere reconsidered the novel invention of the wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons of debates that whether we should reinvent the wheel or not. Many people agree with it while others disagree. Believers suggest it’s a good way to think more critically and provide a better invention, while critics say why should we recreate something which is already there. They both are correct at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to understand that we don’t reinvent just for the sake of reinvention instead we should comprehend the situation and do the appropriate thing. For example, you run a company which sells Peanut Butter and you want to go online. Then there is no need to invent a way to interact online instead you can use online resources. But if you want to improve consistency of Peanut Butter then you might have to reinvent the wheel, breakdown each step in order to optimize each step of the process. This is how the peanut butter industry will progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t reinvent the wheel because you can do it within minutes instead do it because you can develop a better, faster and optimized solution. Don’t do it just for the sake of doing instead do it because it is your requirement.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/reinvent_the_wheel.png&quot; height=&quot;28%&quot; width=&quot;28%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The notion of not reinventing the wheel is popular in the programming world, which I agree with. But sometimes it is necessary to develop things from scratch so that it goes along with your product and does not cause problems. Also, if someone is trying to reinvent the wheel, don’t downtrodden them instead encourage them to approach invention with clear intentions. &lt;strong&gt;We have not run out of ideas and we never will&lt;/strong&gt;, every time you stop someone from redoing an invention, you are shutting down the possibility of the next breakthrough. Even if there is no output, the educational value through reinventing is too significant. So encourage people to reinvent!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Reinvent-the-wheel/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Reinvent-the-wheel/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 030, Ruth Carter: Costume Design </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of Ruth Carter’s episode in Abstract: The Art of Design — a story of the first African-American women to win an Oscar for Best Costume Design for her work in Black Panther in 2019 — Ruth Carter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruth Carter, one of the most famous names in the fashion industry began her journey in college theater. She auditioned for a play but didn’t get it, but the instructor asked her if she wanted to design costumes. She did not have any formal training in Costume Design but she knew how to navigate around the script. She went to the costume shop, picked up some fabrics and patterns, cut them and designed outfits. Before long, production after production, she became costume designer at her university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Ruth Carter, fashion was an important part of costume designing but the more important part was storytelling — the process of taking an idea and bringing it to life. She tells the story of the character, its background, its culture and what makes them themselves. It isn’t just about how the dress is perceived by others but her designs have an aura to light up the personality of the people and at the same time make them comfortable in their costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From college theater to films, her idea to design through the costumes has been spiritualistic. How does Ruth design them? She first breaks down the script and forms the visual of the story — the culture, the timeline, the genre, everything. She develops an imaginary draft of the costumes to support the wonderments of the script to depict the richness of the script. Next step is to select the fabrics, lining, button, trim and combine them to narrate the theme of the script. Then come the nuts and bolts of what these ideas really look like, mood boards are full of fabric swatches, magazine cutouts,  illustrations, everything that gives inspiration. Designed clothes are now to be tried on, thus fitting rooms are often known as the transformation room. She always looks for improvement in her design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her early life, she had seen a derogatory image of blacks in cinema. Being a costume designer, she wanted to support greater story, story of times, story of people. And to her amazement, Spike Lee asked her to debut in Do the Right Thing, a movie in which Ruth brought out the African Pop Culture — vibrant crop top, necklaces, shorts. She loved to research the colors of times, the economics of the time, how people lived in those times, everything about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruth’s dynamism to understand people was instilled by her mother. Her mother taught her to empathize with people which later helped her to understand people deeply. Ruth observes the style of people walking down the street and interprets their culture, their beginning, what they care about. 
In 2019, Ruth got the opportunity to create the world of Black Panther. It was an immense task to explore the reigns of ancient indigenous tribes around Africa which are vast resources of Artistic ideas. She infused the cultural and African diaspora with the realm of fantasy and futuristic world of Black Panther. Introduction of Killmonger in western contemporary dress to Dora Milaje’s ethnic colors of Africa depicted ethnic groups of Wakanda and defined colonialism. She was awarded an Oscar for her artistic and well-defined designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her work has always left people awestruck. She brings humanity, emotionality to life through her clothes in a way that they are not only historically accurate but that can imagine black lives that the history books have told us wasn’t possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Ruth-Carter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Ruth-Carter/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
