<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 11:23:09 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 11:23:09 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 010, Battle of Laziest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sloth vs Koala — These two might make you super sleepy. Don’t take out your pillows just yet. Instead, grab a coffee. Don’t worry, you ain’t gonna miss anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sloths are low energy loafers, inhabitant to Central and South America. These are drowsy tree-dwellers who sleep 15 hours a day and barely move even when awake. They are so snail-paced that they grow algae on their skin, it makes them less noticeable to predators. If you groom Sloths, thousands of moths might fly out. In fact, when they groom themselves, they move their fingers so slow that the moths have no difficulty keeping up with the pace. Once every week, they come down to defecate and cover their poop with leaves. While on ground, they move slowly by digging their front claws into the dirt and dragging their bodies. Despite the fact that they don’t do much, sloth has a constant smile on the face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next contestant is Koala. Often known as Koala-bear, it is barely related to the bear family, instead Koala belongs to Marsupials family. These sleepy-headed creatures doze off for 18 hrs a day. Found in Australia, these convenient eaters hardly leave the Eucalyptus tree where they get endless supply of their favorite food — Eucalyptus leaves. This means less time searching for food  and more time for snoring. Koalas might not be the smartest animal but they are cute, cuddly and extremely photogenic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does it mean laziness contributes to happiness? :p&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these beings are either sleeping or daydreaming. But who is the winner? Umm, None. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/proishan11&quot;&gt;Ishan Singh&lt;/a&gt;, a friend of mine with a weird hairdo. He has achieved new heights of laziness in this lockdown. He hasn’t left the sofa in a while and has developed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lissencephaly&quot;&gt;smooth brain&lt;/a&gt;. Reaching this new feat of idleness, sloth and koala are no competition to him. As a matter of fact, he has moved beyond the illusions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, get back to your fast paced schedules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. Sadly, earlier this year many Koalas were killed because of Australian Fire.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Battle-of-laziest/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Battle-of-laziest/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 009, Dark Matter and Dark Energy : the holding forces</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever Since the Big Bang, our Universe is expanding and reaching new feat. If gravity was playing its role, the universe would have collapsed. Also, gravity cannot explain the high rotation speed of the galaxies. Either the gravity behaves in an odd fashion or there might be some matter in the Universe that holds everything together while the Universe is expanding. Indeed there exists a substance termed as Dark Matter. Dark matter is the most mysterious yet ubiquitous substance in the Universe. Our Universe has around 68% dark energy, 37% Dark Matter. The rest 5% is everything on Earth, everything ever observed by instruments and all normal material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I feel so tiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 5 basic elements — Space, Air, Fire, Water, and Earth — of the material world, Dark Matter could not be seen, felt, smelt or tasted. In fact, It does not even interact with electromagnetic waves. This means it does not absorb, reflect or emit light, making it more difficult to spot. Researchers have seen some potential interaction with gravitational forces. What is it? As of now, we know more about what it isn’t than what it is. Dark Matter isn’t anti matter, otherwise it would have produced gamma rays when annihilated with normal matter. Neither is it a black hole, or failed stars or clouds of gas or anything else that can be made from normal matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations are trying to figure out its presence to understand more about the Universe. Scientists have installed sensitive sensors under the Earth to see if Dark Matter interacts with classical elements. Similarly, Satellites, through a special Gamma Ray Telescope, traces the energy imprints of dark matter collision. Moreover, at CERN, researches are smashing normal particles together inside the Large Hadron Collider just to check if there is subsequent change in the property of the material inside. Although the results aren’t successful, we understand more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several theories explaining dark matter. Albert Einstein first explained it as the property of the space, suggesting empty space is not nothing. Later, in one version of Einstein’s gravity theory, he proposed a cosmological constant. Through cosmological constant, he predicted that “empty space” can possess its own energy and would not be diluted. As more space comes, more energy will be generated. This defines the ever expanding nature of the Universe. No one actually understood why cosmological constant is even there. Another theory, derived from Quantum theory of matter, proposed that empty space is made of virtual particles that continually form and disappear. But using this theory, when the energy of dark matter was calculated, it was wrong by an order of 10&lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;. There are other incomplete theories which, at the end, lead to nothing. So, the mystery remains unrevealed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark Matter is a mystery that we want to understand. Demystifying it would be a key to a whole new understanding of physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dark Matter matters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Dark-Matter-and-Dark-energy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Dark-Matter-and-Dark-energy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 008, Being One</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Don’t overthink, there is nothing whimsical, scary, poetic, it’s just a post about number one. No no no, not about number one but about NUMBER 1. Ugh! It’s just too hard. Nevermind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One is the loneliest number” is not just a song but a truth in the world of Mathematics. 1 is no fun to play with. Multiplying and dividing by one is so underwhelming. Mathematically, it is called “unity” and it has even more strange properties — the square root of one is one. With all this unlikeliness, one wasn’t even considered as a number for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle, Euclid and many of the founding fathers of Mathematics did not consider one as a number. Why? They reasoned that the number is “multitude composed of units”. Under this definition, one is not a number but the seed for a number. And I used to feel I am a sufferer of FOMO. But this isn’t the end. In Contemporary world, when one is considered as a number there are other hustles. Historically, One has been on and off the hook of prime numbers list. With all the properties of being a prime, mathematicians suggested one does not preserve the uniqueness of the factorization. Finally, The fundamental theorem of arithmetic which states that “Every positive integer can be represented as the product of prime numbers.” suggested the world of mathematics to exclude one from the definition of prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[6 = 2\times 3\]
\[6 = 3\times 2\]
\[6 = 1\times 2 \times 3\]
\[6 = 1\times 1\times 2 \times 3\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two are unique factorization but latter two aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;One is the loneliest number you will ever do.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might be the loneliest number but one was never the loser. It has overpowered the world of technology along with zero —  binary notation. No number can be formed without the approval of one. In Grandi’s series when one was added and subtracted infinitely to add up to \(\frac{1}{2}\), made one quite confused about its existence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[S = 1-1+1-1+1-1+…\]
\[1-S = 1 - (1-1+1-1…..) = S\]
\[1-S = S\]
\[S = \frac{1}{2}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One” might as well have its own problems, but it is ruling the world with peace. Next time you feel low or anxious or sad, think about the struggles of one — From not even getting considered as a number to being one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Being-One/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Being-One/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 007, Cyberbullying</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Bullying is someone using their power to hurt someone physically, mentally or socially, it is much more worse than being mean. But with technologies in hand you don’t need to be powerful to harass anyone — And I present to you Cyberbullying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, there are various ways of cyberbullying, sending, posting or sharing negative, wrong information about anyone. These depraved activities to harass or defame someone makes the victim angry, sad, anxious, depressed and oftentimes suicidal which takes toll upon their mental health over years. Mostly, teenagers are either victims or perpetrators of cyberbullying. Their developing prefrontal cortex — a part of the brain which helps in making decisions and controlling impulses — often provokes them to take stupid decisions when poked even slightly. Ever Since we are in the middle of the pandemic, Gen Z’s are spending more time scrolling Instagram, Facebook, Snapchat for personal or educational purposes, internet hate has increased and so has cyberbullying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could happen anytime, anywhere leaving the victim with no place to feel safe. Victims are tormented by the hate they get through messages or through the hate page solely dedicated to trashing a person. Yes, you read it correct, purposely built HATE PAGES. With the anonymity features of social media platforms the picture has become scarier, the sufferers do not know who is organizing the attacks. Presence of these toxicities makes me feel queasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberbullying is more pernicious when it comes to children who do not have the resilience to deal hatred like an adult. Just because it takes place over the internet and does not have physical threat parents generally ignore it. This leaves the victim in a timid spot. This is why 9 out of 10 of the cyberbullied do not tell their guardians about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media platforms are trying to curb floods of toxic, extreme content and misinformation. Instagram, which has the most number of young audiences, is using machine learning algorithms to detect cyberbullying in photos and captions. Parents should start to talk to their kids about cyberbullying. Products like “&lt;a href=&quot;www.rethinkwords.com&quot;&gt;ReThink&lt;/a&gt;” are developing solutions to stop cyberbullying before the damage is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Research shows that when adolescents are alerted to rethink their decision, they change their minds 93% of the time. Using ReThink™, the overall willingness of an adolescent to post an offensive message reduced from 71% to 4%.&lt;br /&gt;
— Trisha Prabhu, Inventer ReThink&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberbullying is as heinous a crime. Awareness is the key to prevent from getting harassed online. Children should be made aware about the consequences of sharing personal information on the internet. It cannot be stopped until everyone takes responsibility to report any of such behaviour.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;”Stop ignoring cyberbullying. Let’s make internet a better place!”&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cyberbullying/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cyberbullying/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 006, Clickbaits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before starting this post, I watched a video on “Advertisements vs Reality” not for research purpose but *CLICKBAIT* — you will be happy to know I have achieved enlightenment. If I could have achieved enlightenment by clicking on the clickbaits, I would be a genius today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These catchy headlines are all over the place — news articles, Youtube, social media posts. Clickbaits have infiltrated the internet and have made the internet frustrating. The science of virality, clickbait, is analogous to alchemy that turns lead to gold. Clickbaits play along with our emotions, providing us comfort. But clickbaits are not just in your head — digital marketers, writers, editors play a role all along to understand the behavioural sciences of humans. These folks have mastered the skills to produce compelling clickbaits to grab your attention. While you might feel sadness, anger and fear, you still somehow click on the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pleasure of dopamine high keeps us motivated to constantly be aroused by clickbaits and fall into the pitfall, following links repeatedly. Through every compelling clickbait we click we activate a pathway for dopamine. Dopamine is released and creates an itch that can be fed by the promised clickbait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clickbait, noun: Things I don’t like on the Internet.
— Joshua Benton, Nieman Journalism lab at Harvard University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have you opened Youtube just to watch a single video but ended up watching more? The reason is clickbaits, it is taking your time as well as mental resources without your knowledge. Social media feeds are full of over-promising headlines. Once you start to ingest articles/videos you anticipate that you are learning something. Ever wondered how credible these clickbaits are? The studies in these articles often limit many factors like geographic location, age, gender. Thus they cannot provide a generalized truth. To mitigate this issue consumers should take a look at the case study on which the article is reporting on and read many studies. But this task of digging the truth is often not so appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the internet is that everyone wants your attention. And as long as there are clickbaits people will continue to click on it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Clickbaits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Clickbaits/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 005, Sneakers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Air Jordan, Yeezys, PUMA Suede, Converse, Vans — Ring a bell? Sneakers. Australians call them “runners”. The British know them as “trainers” and Americans address them as “tennis shoes” or “sneakers’. Whatever you call them, these rubber-soled, casual shoes are worn by billions of people around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago Sneakers were considered ungentlemanly and were part of alternative society, but now it has totally taken over the fashion industry. Sneakers are considered art. These youth-cultured streetwears are worn on runways, red carpets, workplaces and where not. Sneakers are versatile staples which go with everything. This is partly because of the evolution in our professional lives. There are barely any jobs which require the employee to be suited and booted. Engineers, journalists, teachers, stylists etc are far more likely to wear sneakers than a pair of heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the glamour associated with sneakers, people are obsessed about them. There are sneakerheads with a collection of more than 1000 pairs of sneakers. Sneaker collection is a real thing. Have you seen people queue to buy the latest iPhone — sneakerheads camp outside the sneaker store for days before the sale, and these sales happen way more often. More interestingly, a few minutes after the sale, thousands of these pairs are on eBay for two or three times the retail price. The global sneaker market was valued at 70.1 billion USD in 2018 and is expected to be 108 billion USD by the end of 2025. This craziness is so intense that people have created their own sneaker portfolios to manage their sneaker prices. Is this addiction more like drugs or stocks? Sneakers are a legal and accessible investment opportunity. Sneakers have their own democratized, yet unregulated, stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To meet these crazy demands, companies have to increase the production. But making shoes has become more complicated, more labor intensive and in some ways more dangerous. The heel insole, midsole and upper layer are made up of synthetic textiles. Mining the fossil fuels to develop the textiles generates tons of greenhouse gas and uses lots of energy. The outer sole is made of synthetic blend of natural rubber. Next, sneakers are composed of several discrete parts which are manufactured at different locations to make it cheap. But the transportation of these parts to the assembly line emits even more carcinogenic gases. Once all components arrive at the assembly line they are cut, melted, baked, cooled, glued and then stitched which accounts for the more carbon footprint. Ever Since all the parts are glued so tightly that it is almost impossible to recycle them. Either they are burnt or left in landfills where it takes them thousands of years to degrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, sneakers are rendered as art and have a cult status. But we need to balance our love for sneakers with sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sneakers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sneakers/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 004, First Principle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it overwhelming to break down a complicated problem into basic elements? Not anymore. First Principle to the rescue. Reasoning with first principle helps you break down the problem into small bite-sized steps and then reassemble them from ground. It is one of the best ways to learn to think for yourself, improve your creativity and speed up the process. This approach was introduced by Aristotle and is now used by Elon Musk and many visionaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easier to think in terms of analogy than first principles but first principles deals with more fundamental aspects. What that really means is to boil things down to fundamental truth and then reason up from there. Thus, reasoning by first principle removes impurity of assumptions and convention, leaving us with essentials. These essentials allow us to see where reasoning with analogy would leave us ashtray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider an example, people used to say batteries will be expensive but someone broke battery down into its components and optimized its cost. That is because the first principle helps in driving innovation which in turn leads to looking at things from different perspectives. It has a tremendous effect on people’s ability to make decisions and foster changes. If we never learn to take something apart, test the assumption and reconstruct it, we will get stuck in what other people told us — trapped in the way things have always been. The reason it is a revolutionary idea is, most of the people spend most of their time looking on the surface. But the ideas are engraved within the fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To understand is to know what to do.” — Wittgenstein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates, who is famous for laying the foundation for modern Western Philosophy, developed a questioning system to establish first principle. Socratic questioning is a stringent process and illuminates the importance of questioning in learning. Following steps are taken in the process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarifying thinking and explaining the origin of ideas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Challenging the assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing evidences on basis of truth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Considering alternative perspective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring implication and consequences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Questioning the original question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process helps you take off the blinds and builds something that lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasoning through analogy is definitely easier but reasoning through first principle helps you develop better understanding of the fundamental. This is what makes the best resource for creative thinking.  Thinking in first principles allows you to look at the world in a different way, adapt to the changing environment and seize the opportunity others can’t. So next time you are confused about a decision and how to break it down — The First Principle.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/First-Principle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/First-Principle/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 003, Are we inside simulation?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As absurd as this question sounds, the more interesting it is. The question that we are the characters of a very advanced computer civilization. Isn’t it awesome? Simulation hypothesis is an idea that the physical world we live in, including the Earth and rest of the world is a computer simulation. You can think of it as a high resolution, first person conscious video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature, the Earth, the Universe is governed by a set of mathematical rules, a lot of which we are not even aware of. Moreover, the sub atomicity proves that everything is broken up into pieces just like pixels in video games. From the first video game Pong to today, our computer games have evolved and become more realistic. As the computing power will grow, the quality of games will become more palpable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can reach such technological advancement to create a simulation so powerful that it is similar to our real world then it would be a very strong proof that we are inside a simulation — a simulation creating a simulation. The chances are that our creator(s) are also part of some other simulation. Infact, it gives a radical alternative to the current model of reality, resulting in an infinite Universe. Each subsequent simulation will be less and less technologically advanced — they just won’t be able to match their creators in advancing technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait, but of what use would a simulation be? Just like we use computers to perform all kinds of mathematical calculations, in a similar way our brains perform tons and tons of operation per second. With all the organisms around the Universe, our creator must be drawing lots and lots of power from our Universe. Also, a simulated Universe could be designed for the eventual rise of life, that is experimenting with the components and parameters to make the life of the creator better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you must be wondering how can we confirm if we are in a simulation? How many times have you witnessed a miracle or coincidence? This might be a glitch in the computer program we are living in. Softwares get bugs and updates all the time which are often rolled out in our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, there is a lot we need to discover and a lot we need to understand before we reach a point where we can model the universe of our own and unleash the truth. This discovery will give rise to a myriad of questions or it might make things simpler, just like when Corpenicus realised Earth was not the center of the Universe. Afterall, it is still a mystery if we are even real.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Are-We-Inside-simulation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Are-We-Inside-simulation/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 002, Rubik's Cube</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“What’s that red, blue, yellow twisty toy am I fidgeting with? Rubik’s Cube? Those who know me know how gaga I am for Rubik’s Cube.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did Hungarian Professor Erno Rubik know when he invented rubik’s cube from wooden blocks and paper clips that his invention would be so popular. It’s been a long time since I was first gifted with a Rubik’s Cube. My father gifted me one he bought from the Aligarh Exhibition when I was 12 or 13 years old. Like many school going kids I was enamored by the Rubik’s Cube but could barely even solve 1 layer. One day, in frustration, I broke the cube but later that day I joined those pieces together and that’s how I solved the cube for the first time but never touched it again. Up until freshman year at college where I bought a decent cube and again, I started the quest to figure out 1 of the 43 quintillion total possibilities without any help. Baffled, I was on the verge to break the cube when a cousin of mine told me the algorithm to solve it. Delhi wasn’t far, I learned to solve the cube in 2 days and within a week I memorized the basic algorithm and was able to solve it in less than 3 minutes. After a month of practice, my average speed was about a minute or so but I wasn’t satisfied by the algorithm and started to look for a faster alternative for speed cubing. I started to watch youtube tutorials endlessly and over some time my speed gradually improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was learning gradually, I wanted to feed my curiosity to solve different types of Rubik’s Cube. The 5X5X5 and Mirror cube were very similar to 3X3X3 where the centerpiece is directly connected to the scaffold which means the center won’t move. But in 4X4X4, also known as Rubik’s Revenge, there are no fixed centerpiece, this makes it more tricky. Axis Cube is a mod of 3X3X3 cube with unequal divisions, which means a scrambled Axis Cube won’t be cubical in shape. The main hustle with Axis Cube is to figure out center, edge and corner parts. And then comes Megaminx, a dodecahedron based puzzle similar to Rubik’s Cube with 50 separate pieces and 12 different colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/rubiksCube.jpg&quot; height=&quot;80%&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I learned about it, the more I wanted to know about it. All the algorithms slowly became trivial when I started understanding the mathematics of Rubik’s Cube. I am always fascinated by how many secrets Rubik’s cube holds. Out of all these the most interesting is the God’s number which tells the maximum number of steps required to solve a Rubik’s Cube is 20 despite the configuration. It is called so because you have to be some kind of omniscient to figure out these moves. Out of 43 quintillion possibilities only 490 million (1.14*10&lt;sup&gt;-9&lt;/sup&gt; %) requires a maximum of 20 moves to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, Rubiks Cube has added lots of positivity in my life. Sometimes, this simplistic yet complex toy acts as a de-stresser, providing a distraction from life. Other times, it challenges me to draw out more secrets. But it always satisfies my inner self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;Next time you see a Rubik's Cube, grab it and try solving it. It's fun, it's meditative, it's amazing.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Rubiks-Cube/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Rubiks-Cube/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 001, What I learnt from characters of F.R.I.E.N.D.S</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank You &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/IramMahe&quot;&gt;Mahe&lt;/a&gt; for the edits.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
I know what you thinking; “Oh, not another FRIENDS fan!!!” But who cares what you think? I am a F.R.I.E.N.D.S fan and I am going to write about it.  I have been a fan ever since I first watched these 6 reckless adults trying to make the best out of their beautifully troublesome and oh-so-happening life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obsessive-compulsive natured Monica, dim-witted yet caring Joey, Rachel: self centered but always trying to be a good friend, Phoebe-the gaga with a child’s heart, clumsy but intelligent Ross, and of course Chandler, the socially awkward king of sarcasm; I wanted to be friends with each one of them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their starkly different natures all harmonized in a perfect symphony. I binge watch F.R.I.E.N.D.S on a daily basis. 
I feel happy, I watch FRIENDS. I am sad, I watch FRIENDS.  I am fearful, disgusted, angry or surprised I watch FRIENDS. I watch FRIENDS all the time. 
Today I ended up pondering  what each character of FRIENDS taught me. 
This is what I came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ross&lt;/strong&gt; : “Hi” — I might kill myself. With a doctorate degree and three divorces, Ross taught me UNAGI * does the touching-forehead-with-index-finger action *. In all seriousness, Ross has been a caring, polite and a kind person. He was always there to help when something went wrong. His intelligence and nerd weirdness never stops him from forming valuable relationships. Ross proved that brainy is the new sexy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monica&lt;/strong&gt; : A cleanliness freak — “I know” —  glued the entire group as family. I think she is the mother of the group and like mothers sometimes are,  she can be domineering and overbearing. Why not? She taught us that it’s alright to let people down just to be yourself. Her habit of orderliness and planning tells us that always having a plan is the best way to live your life(well, it’s nice to think so). And the most important thing; food is truly the best thing in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chandler&lt;/strong&gt; : Hands down, Chandler has evolved the most, from being the most vulnerable to his endless love towards Monica, Chandler taught us how to love. Through his never ending witty remarks and socially awkward puns he told us the best thing you can give someone is a good laugh. The guy has one liners for every damned situation and he knows how to diffuse tension in the room. I try to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rachel&lt;/strong&gt; : From leaving her fiancé and being a spoiled brat to being offered a position at Louis Vuitton in Paris, Rachel taught me that it is never too late. Her role as waitress narrates that sometimes one has to settle for a job one dislikes. Rachel’s character delivered that materialism isn’t the key to happiness but being sassy can make you feel good. Most importantly, she taught me that true love can withstand a great deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phoebe&lt;/strong&gt; : “Smelly Cat, Smelly Cat, what are they feeding you” — I believe you must have sung it. She is by far my most favorite character because of her freaky and weird childlike spirit. Her oddly realistic guitar sessions have been a therapy for me. Her bizarre pseudo-scientific theory to explain actually got me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joey&lt;/strong&gt; : “How you doin’..?” — Joey is good natured  but not so bright. He loves food and sex — “If you had to, what would you give up, food or sex? I want girls on bread”. Haha. Even thinking of that scene, I crack up! Was it his dim-witted nature that made him so optimistic and so confident of his talents? I learnt from Joey to  have faith in myself even when no one else did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have felt their heart break and I have rejoiced in their joy.
I have cried with them. I have sat on that orange couch and have laughed with them.&lt;br /&gt;
These 6 weirdos are not just characters for me, they are my own best friends.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/What-i-learnt-from-friends/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/What-i-learnt-from-friends/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
