<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 12:48:02 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 12:48:02 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 050, Emoji — 😀 😒 🤥 💀  👾 🤖 🎃 😺</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, July 17 was Emoji Day. So I decided to write about it. July 17 is marked as emoji day because Apple calendar emoji has the same date mentioned on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From cave paintings to emoji — we have come a long way. With every passing day, as we evolve new emojis are introduced. Emojis are the future of language and semiotics. Much like punctuations, emoji’s have made the conversations hasslefree. Well, thinking about conversation without emoji is difficult for us. Emoji makes the conversation interesting and helps us to express ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, there were emoticons — :-) and :-( and :-P. For the most part, they were used in chat rooms in the 1990s. The first emoji was created by Japanese artist Shigetaka Kurita in 1999. Kurita wanted to design an attractive interface to convey information in a simple way. So Kurita sketched 12-by-12 pixel images that could be selected from the keyboard-like grid and then sent on to mobile and pages. Kurita’s original 176 emoji’s — now part of the permanent collection of the New York Museum of Modern Art — had symbols to characterise emotions, weather, traffic, technology and phases of the moon. As of March 2020, Unicode Consortium — which acts as the UN for text and signs — has approved 3304 emojis. Now more than 92 percent of the people online use emoji, and one-third use on a daily basis. This trend of emoji began when Apple added emojis to iOS keyboard in 2008. Two years later, Android also unveiled an emoji keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the language of texting changed. In 2015, Oxford Dictionary crowned “Face with Tears of Joy” as the word of the year. This was the first time that an emoji became a linguistic champion. Meanwhile All the emojis are pixels of information. Emoji roots from the Japanese word “e” which means picture and “moji” which means character. Essentially, the emojis are images designed to narrate a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year designers submit new emojis to the Unicode Consortium which are properly testified before being rolled out. The fundamental improvement in the emoji vocabulary is based on the incorporation of culture of underrepresented communities. As these emojis come up we understand something about the cultural priorities and types of people who are included in forming this digital growing age. Anyone can submit a proposal to add a new emoji. Unicode asks for proper documentation, an explanation of why and how people will use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Text is the most powerful, go-to communication tool. Emojis are the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Emoji/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Emoji/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 049, Diamonds</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From the mines of Aikhal, Russia to the hands of your loved ones. “A diamond is forever” — De Beers, during the diamond monopoly, made it the epitome of love. The marketing tactic by De Beers has made diamonds reach the mark they are at now. Once they monopolized the diamond market, they soon controlled its supply. Often this marketing campaign is considered as the most successful campaign ever. Believe me, diamonds are not investments. They re-sell at 25-30% of their actual worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree, unlike several other gems, Diamonds are forged deep inside the Earth’s crust under very high pressure and temperature which makes it rare and hence making it expensive. But given the technological advancements diamond can be fabricated in the lab as well. Diamond is an allotrope of carbon just like graphite. But they both have different atom alignment which gives them different properties. In the lab, graphite is exposed to hundreds of tonnes of pressure which converts graphite to diamond. Compared to the diamonds formed under the earth’s crust, the diamonds formed in the lab are crystal clear and are aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do diamonds surface? Diamonds are formed 100-150 km beneath the earth’s surface and reside at volcanic magma chambers. When a volcano erupts, a rare type of magma, kimberlite, is erupted which when cooled form diamonds. These diamonds age between 1 billion to 3.5 billion years.  But these diamonds have impurities which are introduced in the lattice when they are being formed. Although these discrepancies make them ugly, they are very useful for scientists. These inconsistencies help in understanding and advancing the study of deeper earth. These marvels of the natural world have the highest hardness and thermal conductivity. These properties are utilized in major industrial applications such as cutting and polishing tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, Diamonds for jewelry requires a diamond Certification. Labs like GIA, AGS, IGI, EGL, GSI, and HRD provide a certificate which describes diamond and its characteristics. Color, Clarity, length and width is scrutinized by the professionals under the microscope. A diamond’s 4C’s represent the four main components of its beauty and structure: Cut, Color, Clarity and Carat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From deep blues to the stunning red, diamonds are sparkling crystals which are a sign of royalism and capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Diamonds/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Diamonds/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 048, Deep Generative Modeling of LiDAR Data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the summary of the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.01180&quot;&gt;Deep Generative Modeling of LiDAR Data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper covers the niche problem of generative modeling on lidar scans. Often, the data through the sensor is corrupted or has some inconsistencies. This might lead to a tumultuous behaviour within the robot thus affecting the output. To address this problem, developing an intelligent system is an important mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative modeling has shown massive growth in images but it is still in its toddler stages compared to 3D and lidar data. Thus, the authors have devised to project the 3D lidar sensory data to a 2D grid. The spherical lidar data is converted to a 2D grid through a two-step process. Step 1, the N (x,y,z) points are clustered into H parts on the basis of the angle of elevation. Points with the same angle of elevation buckets into the same cluster. In the next step, the 360 degree plane is divided into W parts. This gives us a grid of H x W. Information of each cell is accumulated into a tensor of size 3 — H x W x 3. This data can be easily converted to the polar coordinate system. The devised technique is used on the KITTI dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the data is prepared, the baselines are developed on AtlasNet using the KITTI data without any preprocessing. Paper talks about conditional and unconditional generation. In conditional generation the data is slightly tampered with some noise, here Gaussian Noise, and then remodeled to reconstruct the input intelligently. Since the modeling is not based on sampling but instead on reconstruction, VAE and AE are used. Simultaneously, for unconditional generation, GANs are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rigorous evaluation criteria for generative modeling is still an open problem. But here the authors have used the Earth Mover metric — optimal transport problem —  and Chamfer distance. Moreso, for training parameters they have randomly selected learning rate, latent dimensions and batch size and experimented with 10 different configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed adversarial network can produce highly realistic images. Also VAE for lidar data provides a very robust solution to deal with noisy data.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Lidar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Lidar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 047, Avatar : The Last Airbender</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I started to watch Avatar : The Last Airbender, when Netflix &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/netflix/status/1261419683116249089?lang=en&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; about it in May. Like any other series, I followed it at snail’s pace but without striking my  attention I endlessly binged all three seasons. It is an animated adventure series which was originally aired for three seasons on Nickelodeon during 2005-2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar: The Last Airbender takes place in a fantasy world set up in Eastern Culture. The undertones of the series follow the Ancient Chinese philosophy of Yin and Yang. Human civilization is divided into four nations : Air, Water, Earth and Fire. Each nation has its natural element, on the basis of its society, and within each nation exist people known as “benders” who have the innate power to play and the ability to control and manipulate elements of their nation. The show’s creator has assigned each bending style its own martial art form. This world is menaced by Fire Nation, who attacks and exploits every other nation and land to form a totalitarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar can restore balance to nature, who in correspondence of the story is reborn as a different member of the four nations. During its lifetime, Avatar has to master the prowess of all the four elements. In this series, Avatar is a 12 year old monk named Aang, who was born to two Air Nomads. Shortly before the 100 years of war, Aang froze in an iceberg for hundred years. He emerged, still biologically 12 years old, into the world engulfed by war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aang teams up with two members of the southern water tribe — Katara, the waterbender and Sokka. They travel the world in the search of masters of elements to end the war. Paralleling this, Zuko, abandoned prince of Fire nation aimed to defeat and capture Avatar and restore his pride. Meanwhile, Aang meets secondary characters who helped him master all the elements to bring back harmony to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aang and his friends along with his six-legged flying bison practiced martial arts and went on expeditions. The world of the show is full of fanciful places — A jungle denser than amazon, rocky terrain, upside-down temples carved under cliffs, a vast desert with a library of limitless knowledge, and even an island on the back of a beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar managed to embrace all the movements taught by the masters while still following his cultural appropriation. Being a monk he has never killed any living being. As Sozin’s Comet approaches Earth, the fire nation fledged to full power and aimed to capture the world. Worried he might have to kill Firelord, Aang meditated into Avatar State to gain knowledge of all the past Avatars. Confused by the wisdom but determined by his principles, Aang refuses to kill Firelord Ozai. Aang used elemental bending to take away Ozai’s firebending power, removing his ability to wage war. This marked the end of the war. During the coronation, Prince Zuko, who fought for purity promised to aid the world in the postwar reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avatar the last airbender is full of small acts of kindness. It paints the value of hope and empathy while in the world which is full of terrible things — war, imperialism, genocide. Although the world does not face a threat as clear as fire nation, that doesn’t mean that there aren’t issues that are meant to be addressed — climate change, corruption, political divides. Aang and his friends have shown us that despite the scale of our world’s issue, we all play a role in solving them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Avatar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Avatar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 046, Pandemic and Exams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Exam and Election season in India are amazing. These two seasons cause more deaths and devastation than any other, especially the former one. Thank You Indian society for making students feel bad about themselves. Thank You for forcing them to commit suicide. Thank You for forcing them to break their mental peace. Thank You for making them feel horrible. Aha! Let’s add a topping on it, exams during a pandemic. It was fine until the assignments but exams amidst this pandemic are going to be a hodgepodge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of exams is to test students what they are taught. It gives you the ability to stay focused under pressure. It brushes your skill. I believe it does but being locked in the house for more than 100 days doesn’t make the situation better despite it makes it worse. When the lockdown was imposed I planned to take on cutting things off my bucket list. I am sure all you must have thought that way but slowly the stress, anxiety, fear, pressure started to build up. Everyone is on the verge of mental breakdown. The surrounding is depressed. The world is depressed. The world is becoming hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we taking exams? Are we even taught anything? Irregular classes, poor internet, irritated students and teachers — the feudal system. The world is going down, the economy is crashing, protests are being held, police brutality is peaking and most importantly, people are dying because of COVID-19. People are scared. Even the calmest of the minds are flipping out. What do you expect from young adults? Their prefrontal cortex is not developed. This compromises to rageful decisions, sloppy behaviour, recklessness, impulsive nature and disturbed brain. These are the future of the nation. While they are gradually slipping into the cruel world, it’s hard for them to understand the nature of people, making them anxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions of UGC has contributed more to this. Students who are already under pressure are being provided with confusing statements. Authorities have constantly changed their decision in the nick of time. State governments suggested not to hold examinations then UGC, on July 6, issued a notice to conduct examinations of the terminal semester and final year, suggesting to hold exams by September 30. While WHO has passed guidelines suggesting that the worst is yet to come. UGC believes all of it will settle by September 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities have tried mock examinations but thanks to the poor internet infrastructure, the system has been brutally compromised. There is a case of a girl committing suicide because her father couldn’t afford a smartphone for her class. Government is slowly transforming schools and colleges to COVID centers and at the same time asking students to take offline exams. Believe it or not, things are getting out of hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative is to cancel final semester exams while using the average of marks obtained in previous semesters as a proxy of final semester marks. This will meet the guidelines of pandemic and there is nothing to worry about the connectivity because prior examination results are already available. 
While we talked about mental health when Sushant Singh Rajput died, at the same time UGC has forced exams and increased the mental tension of the final year students. Aren’t those officers aware of the fragile and panicky age of young adults, or officers at UGC love the cheap and reliable idea of exams for creating hierarchy in society?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Exams/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Exams/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 045, Game of Life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1970, John Conway published an eclectic paper about cellular automata — the game of life. It is a simulation that chooses how a complex thing like mind can come from a basic set of rules. This simulation consists of a grid, like a chessboard, extending infinitely in all directions. Each lid of the grid can either be lit up or dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cellular Automata&lt;/strong&gt; is a collection of colored cells in a grid like pattern to represent the state of that machine or program. It evolves over time according to the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game of Life is a zero player game, whose evolution depends on the initial stage of the game. Defined on 8 adjacent grid cells, the configuration of the next state depends on the configuration of the given cell and its corresponding neighbour cells. At each step in the time, following transitions can take place:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a cell is alive then it stays alive if it has either 2 or 3 live neighbours.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the cell is dead then it springs to life only in the case that it has 3 live neighbours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial patterns constitute the seed of the system. This elementary cellular automata either blooms out or dies off. It is not necessary the structure becomes complex and intriguing nor is it necessary it must die off, there is a possibility that the structure oscillates and repeats itself every few moves. Block, beehive, loaf, boat — remain static and never change; blinker, toad, beacon oscillates, while glider and lightweight spaceship changes configuration over configuration and repeats the initial seed at different locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_static.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt; --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_oscillate.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt; --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/conway_repeat.png&quot; height=&quot;70%&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behaviour of plants and animals can be better understood by these simple rules. Behaviour that seems intelligent, such as ant colonies might just be simple rules that we don’t understand yet. Traffic problems might be solved by analyzing them with the mathematical tool and breaking it down to fundamental. Computer viruses are also examples of cellular automata. Finding the pattern in these viruses might also be hidden in this life. Human diseases can be cured if we could better understand how cells live and die. Exploring the galaxies could be easier if the machines could be invented that could create a replica of themselves. Game of life helps in understanding all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conway’s game of life is an existential proof that complex and unpredictable nature is possible due to a simple but recursive system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Images from &lt;a href=&quot;https://natureofcode.com/book/chapter-7-cellular-automata/&quot;&gt;Chapter 7: The Nature of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Game-of-life/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Game-of-life/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 044, Sugar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A carbohydrate used to address your loved one because of its sweetness. But sugar is not good for your body, not your loved ones — or maybe but the carbohydrate. Sugar is bitter to you and your body. It has a drug like effect at the center of the brain. Sweet food — just like salty and fatty food — can produce addiction-like effects in the human brain. It makes you lose self-control, drives your anxiety and oftentimes triggers your overeating habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early humans when the food was scarce, sugar acted like a high-calorie food. But now when the food is abundant, it contributes to obesity and diabetes. Overeating alters the brain reward system which in turn drives overeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glucose, Fructose, Sucrose, Maltose, Lactose, Dextrose, Starch are all types of sugar. Check the labels on your food items. Sugar isn’t just in candies and dessert, it’s also added to tomato sauce, yogurt, flavoured water etc. Since sugar is everywhere it’s important to understand how it affects the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever Since it is found everywhere, chances are you are overdoing it. In excess, it negatively affects your body and brain. Eating sugar rewards your brain — dopamine release reward. Whole food doesn’t release as much dopamine as sugar does. Dopamine gives you the feeling of pleasure. Once you get used to it, dopamine regulates your moods. As soon as you eat sugar your blood pressure rises and gives you a quick burst of energy. But as it starts to break and get absorbed in the body you start to get jittery and anxious. In turn, you eat more sugar and this makes the situation worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive sugar causes tooth decay, causes inflammation on the skin and makes skin age faster. The extra insulin in your bloodstream can make walls of arteries grow thicker which in turn gets stiffer, stressing the heart. This passive damage causes heart diseases like heart attack, stroke, heart failure etc. Similarly, Pancreas get overworked while pumping out more and more insulin. Too much sugar can lead to kidney failure. One who consumes more sugar weighs more and we are aware of the downsides of obesity. Each of these exploits your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, think about all the different kinds of sugar. Each one is unique but each one causes a dopamine trigger making it more addictive. In this way, excessive sugar acts like a drug.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Sugar/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 043, Cannabis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Marijuana, Weed, 420, Ganjha, Kush, Pot, Hemp — whatever you want to call it. There are millions of names for Cannabis and there are millions of people who smoke it everyday. Weed has been an integral part of religion and society of India. For a long time Indians used cannabis freely. Its use is also mentioned in Atharvaveda and Ayurveda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A verse from Atharvaveda. Book 11, Hymn 8 (or 6), Verse 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;पञ्च राज्यानि वीरुधां सोमश्रेष्ठानि ब्रूमः। दर्भो भङ्गो यवः सह ते नो मुञ्चन्त्व् अंहसः॥&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To the five kingdoms of the plants which Soma rules as Lord we speak.
Darbha, hemp, barley, mighty power: may these deliver us from woe. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/cannabis-one-sacred-plant-atharva-veda-sindhu-karpakal&quot;&gt;[Source]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayurveda suggests that the medicinal benefits of marijuana can be used as the treatment against psychosis, anxiety, depression. Also, it suggests, taking excessive amounts of marijuana can dry up the body and hence create imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atharvaveda suggests it brings joy. Lord Shiva is often found with a chillum. Most sadhus and pir baba communicate with God via communal smoking session. Bhang thandai is mandatory on Holi and Maha Shivratri as it is the holy offering. For those of you who don’t know, Bhang is a strain of Cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delhi alone consumes 38,260 kg of cannabis every year, making it the third largest consumer in the world, after New York and Karachi. Mumbai ranks sixth with a consumption of 32,400 kg weed. If the government legalises it, cannabis has a wide market and will add a part to GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a stigma around weed in our country. This exists because any substance that affects your brain is considered bad, unhealthy, unprofessional. I am not saying we should legalise it right away but to break the chain and leave it open for a healthy discussion. Marijuana became illegal in India in 1985, under the Narcotics and Psychotropic Act. It was because of two reasons 1) Because of India’s commitment to the International Treaty on Narcotics. 2) Pressure by the United States because of their participation in the “war on drugs”. Instead of regulating its supply, like an economic commodity, the government simply cut it. Slowly it became a taboo to even talk about it. In recent years, legalizing weed for medicinal use has caught lots of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people suggest weed causes psychotic effects — which is not entirely correct. Weed has two major compounds TetraHydroCannabinol (THC) which gives the feeling of ‘high’. And CBD or Cannabidiol which is non-psychoactive. This means CBD can cancel out the psychotic effects of THC. In recent times, recreational weed has a high amount of THC and less levels of CBD, which gives you a good ‘high’. But because of this, people who are dealing with depression or anxiety or Post Traumatic Stress Disorder can have severe panic attacks. That’s why you need a good amount of CBD in your weed. CBD also helps in chronic pain and can help in recovery of cancer patients, treat depression, help people with epilepsy and Attention Deficit Disorder as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is said weed is a ‘gateway drug’. But it is not entirely supported by Science. Instead 9% of the people get addicted to weed compared to 32% and 15% of alcohol and tobacco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being illegal, the peddlers add toxic substances to it. This might actually end up screwing lots of people. And if it’s legalized, the government can actually maintain standards which will not adversely affect the health of people. Government can connect the dots between legalization, commercialization and decriminalization. I think legalizing weed might just do a lot more good than harm. Yes, I am thinking all wrong! Oh, stupid student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do you think it should be legalized or not?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Cannabis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Cannabis/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 042, March Past</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;August 15, Independence day was approaching. Preparation for the national festival was all over the school, I was in class 4. A shy, small, lean but mischievous kid. Annoying the bullies and meddling with them was my favorite pastime. Sneaking through the class as soon as the recess bell rang. Skipping stairs, running in corridors, poking people with rubber, making up stories was a part of school chores. Obviously, studying was the least favorite thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before Independence Day, students, teachers, non-teaching staff everyone was busy with different errands — reciting national anthem, practising cultural dance, coordinating for march past etc. Quizzes, debates, drawing and many more competitions were organized. Just like me, no one wanted to attend classes. I tried my hands on a general knowledge quiz but answered several questions wrong, verdict — not selected. Then the choir, I mispronounced a word in the stanza, I was kicked. Debating and dancing never interested me. Only option left was participating in the parade. It was closest related to the ground activity, perhaps sports. And definitely better than sitting in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 8 classes of 40 minutes each, we spent the last 6 classes on ground practising the march past, perfecting the leg moment, arm rotation, keeping the head straight, saluting the flag but mostly fun. We traveled with a ball in a bag. We used to run or play with the ball or hide and seek or just roaming the theater hall or intruding on the stage preparation. Often we were scolded for being late. But modern problems require modern solutions. We used to keep a water bottle with us all the time and whenever our teacher asked us where we were, the water bottle rescued us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next was the teacher’s move. They found a solution to deal with the problem. What’s better than a competition between units. There were five units to depict the colors of the flag — Saffron, white, blue for chakra then white and then green. Believe me, teachers are pure genius. They followed the infamous ‘divide and rule’ policy to add aesthetics to the parade. They suggested whichever unit will look coordinated and more disciplined will get an award. It was the misuse of our innocence. Our head boy led the parade with a flagpole in hands and sharpness in his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rehearsals were done. It was August 14, we were all distributed with colored wrist bands to make up for the depicted flag color. Finally, the day had come, Independence Day. We were in school enjoying the patriotic songs on speakers. The ceremony started with our parade. All the marchers were dressed in white colored uniforms and an allocated wrist band. The troops were giving their best to win. But in that smear moment as I glanced through the parade it looked beautiful. A perfect symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marchers sat down as the ceremony progressed. Patriot dance, skits, speeches everything was amazing. But we, marchers, were waiting for the award ceremony. We were waiting to know whose battalion was the best. Award after award, the ceremony ended. In that utter moment, we felt as if we were cheated. The hard work did not go in vain. We had a lot of fun and the laddoos.
Period&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/March-Past/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/March-Past/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 041, Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mathematics-of-generative-adversarial-network&quot;&gt;Mathematics of Generative Adversarial Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/GAN1/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the basics of GANs. In today’s post we will delve right into the mathematics of the GAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the zero sum non cooperative game. If one wins then the other loses. This zero-sum game is also known as a minimax game. Discriminator (\(D\)) is trained to maximize the probability of assigning the correct label to both training examples and samples from Generator (\(G\)). While the generator maximizes probability of (\(D\)) to make mistakes, by minimizing the log of the inverse probability predicted by the discriminator for fake images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GAN.gif&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generator’s distribution \((p_g)\) over \(x\) is defined on prior input noise variable \(p_z(z)\). A neural network framework \(G\) is defined to learn data distribution \(x\). \(G\) maps noise variable to data space as \(G(z; \theta_g)\).&lt;br /&gt;
\(D(x;\theta_d\) outputs a scalar. \(D(x)\) represents probability that \(x\) comes from data whereas in \(D(G(z))\) the \(G(z)\) is from generator network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(G\) is trained to minimize \(\log(1-D(G(z)))\). \(D\) and \(G\) plays minimax game with the value function \(V(G,D)\):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\min_{G}\max_{D}V(D,G) = E_{x\sim p_{data}(x)}[\log(D(x))]\;+\;E_{z\sim p_{z}(z)}[\log(D(G(z)))]\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;center&gt;~ means &quot;has distribution (of)&quot;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adversarial training principle has transformed unsupervised task to supervised task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optimality&quot;&gt;Optimality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle of GANs is based on Nash Equilibrium. This means, theoretically, the algorithm tries to achieve global optimality \(p_g\;=\;p_{data}\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preposition :&lt;/strong&gt; For \(G\) fixed, the optimal discriminator is &lt;br /&gt;
\[D_{G}^{\ast}(x) = \frac{p_{data}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\]
&lt;em&gt;Proof :&lt;/em&gt; To train \(D\) we maximize the value function, keeping \(G\) fixed.&lt;br /&gt;
\[V(G,D) = \int_{x}\;p_{data}(x)\log(D(x))dx\;+\int_{z}p_z(z)\log(1-D(g(z)))dz \]
\[= \int_{x}\;p_{data}(x)\log(D(x))dx\;+\;p_g(x)\log(1-D(x)))dx \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any \(a,b \in R^2\) such that \(a,b \neq {0,0} \). Then the function \(f \; \rightarrow a\log(y) + b\log(1-y)\) achieves maxima at \(\frac{a}{a\;+\;b}\).&lt;br /&gt;
Discriminator is defined within \(supp(p_{data}) \cup supp(p_g)\)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Definition: \(supp(x)\) is the subset of the domain containing those elements that are not mapped to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training objective of discriminator can be reframed as maximum log-likelihood for estimating conditional probability \(P(Y=y\;\vert \;x)\). Thus the minmax equation can be reformulated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[C(G)\; =\; \max_D V(G,D)\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\;+\;E_{z\sim p_{z}}[\log(D_G^\ast(G(z)))]\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\;+\;E_{x\sim p_{g}}[\log(D_G^\ast(x))]\]
\[=\;E_{x\sim p_{data}}\left[\log\left(\frac{p_{data}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\right)\right]\;+\;E_{x\sim p_{g}}\left[\log\left(\frac{p_{g}(x)}{p_{data}(x)\;+\;p_g(x)}\right)\right]\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of Course the aim of GAN is \(p_g\;=\;p_{data}\).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/GAN2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
