<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Square</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 20:15:13 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 20:15:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 031, Reinvent the wheel</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idiomatic Metaphor&lt;/strong&gt; : duplicate a basic method which has already previously been created or optimized by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask any sane person about the greatest discovery of all the time, they will agree that it’s the wheel. The wheel has been reinvented so many times that reinventing the wheel has now become an idiom. If it hadn’t been the plethora of inventors and engineers trying to improve and adapt wheels for various purposes, we would still be traveling in Fred Flintstone’s footmobile.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tenor.gif&quot; height=&quot;60%&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The materials we use have changed from stones to alloys to now carbon-based substances. The content of the wheel has changed, the rim, development of strokes, aerodynamics of the wheel all were possible because someone somewhere reconsidered the novel invention of the wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons of debates that whether we should reinvent the wheel or not. Many people agree with it while others disagree. Believers suggest it’s a good way to think more critically and provide a better invention, while critics say why should we recreate something which is already there. They both are correct at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to understand that we don’t reinvent just for the sake of reinvention instead we should comprehend the situation and do the appropriate thing. For example, you run a company which sells Peanut Butter and you want to go online. Then there is no need to invent a way to interact online instead you can use online resources. But if you want to improve consistency of Peanut Butter then you might have to reinvent the wheel, breakdown each step in order to optimize each step of the process. This is how the peanut butter industry will progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t reinvent the wheel because you can do it within minutes instead do it because you can develop a better, faster and optimized solution. Don’t do it just for the sake of doing instead do it because it is your requirement.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/reinvent_the_wheel.png&quot; height=&quot;28%&quot; width=&quot;28%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The notion of not reinventing the wheel is popular in the programming world, which I agree with. But sometimes it is necessary to develop things from scratch so that it goes along with your product and does not cause problems. Also, if someone is trying to reinvent the wheel, don’t downtrodden them instead encourage them to approach invention with clear intentions. &lt;strong&gt;We have not run out of ideas and we never will&lt;/strong&gt;, every time you stop someone from redoing an invention, you are shutting down the possibility of the next breakthrough. Even if there is no output, the educational value through reinventing is too significant. So encourage people to reinvent!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Reinvent-the-wheel/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Reinvent-the-wheel/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 032, Legend of Lord Ganesha </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ganesha.jpg&quot; height=&quot;30%&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have grown up in a middle-class Hindu family, my pre-teen afternoons during summer vacations were spent learning multiplication tables, eating mangoes, playing Ludo and enjoying the myths in my mother’s lap — legends of Lord Ganesha, Goddess Parvati; stories from Ramayana and Mahabharat. I barely remember any of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Days aren’t the same, but today was different. Just like any other day in quarantine, I was on desk fiddling around with the laptop, mom was scrolling through her WhatsApp. It was not at all odd that she gets all kinds of audio forwards. But today it was, someone was narrating the myths of Lord Ganesha — an anecdote about why every Puja starts with Lord Ganesha’s name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long long ago, while Lord Vishnu and Goddess Lakshmi’s marriage, Lord Ganesha was left in-charge to guard Swargalok. He was tricked to do so because other deities were embarrassed of his physical appearance and his massive diet. The procession went on, when Narad Ji saw Lord Ganesha at the door of Swargalok and asked the reason. Withered Lord Ganesha told his sorrow to Narad Muni. On knowing this Narad suggested Lord Ganesha avenge his respect and devised a plan that would make deities realise Lord Ganesha’s importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Ganesha asked his Mushakraj to dig up the roads that lead to Goddess Lakshmi’s abode. Mushakraj followed the orders and bore the roads. As expected, the deities couldn’t proceed further, the wheels of their chariot got stuck in the earth. Everyone took their measures but the wheel did not move. No one could understand what was going around. A farmer, passing by, decided to help them. The farmer chanted Lord Ganesha’s name and pulled out the carriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmer, being asked by deities, explained that Lord Ganesha’s name has induced strength in him since he is the Remover of Obstacles. Deities realised that there is more to a being than his physical appearance, and they returned to apologize to Lord Ganesha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story tells us to Always stand up for your self-respect. I exchanged smiles, cut a mango and recalled those old days.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Legend-of-Lord-Ganesha/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Legend-of-Lord-Ganesha/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 030, Ruth Carter: Costume Design </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of Ruth Carter’s episode in Abstract: The Art of Design — a story of the first African-American women to win an Oscar for Best Costume Design for her work in Black Panther in 2019 — Ruth Carter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruth Carter, one of the most famous names in the fashion industry began her journey in college theater. She auditioned for a play but didn’t get it, but the instructor asked her if she wanted to design costumes. She did not have any formal training in Costume Design but she knew how to navigate around the script. She went to the costume shop, picked up some fabrics and patterns, cut them and designed outfits. Before long, production after production, she became costume designer at her university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Ruth Carter, fashion was an important part of costume designing but the more important part was storytelling — the process of taking an idea and bringing it to life. She tells the story of the character, its background, its culture and what makes them themselves. It isn’t just about how the dress is perceived by others but her designs have an aura to light up the personality of the people and at the same time make them comfortable in their costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From college theater to films, her idea to design through the costumes has been spiritualistic. How does Ruth design them? She first breaks down the script and forms the visual of the story — the culture, the timeline, the genre, everything. She develops an imaginary draft of the costumes to support the wonderments of the script to depict the richness of the script. Next step is to select the fabrics, lining, button, trim and combine them to narrate the theme of the script. Then come the nuts and bolts of what these ideas really look like, mood boards are full of fabric swatches, magazine cutouts,  illustrations, everything that gives inspiration. Designed clothes are now to be tried on, thus fitting rooms are often known as the transformation room. She always looks for improvement in her design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her early life, she had seen a derogatory image of blacks in cinema. Being a costume designer, she wanted to support greater story, story of times, story of people. And to her amazement, Spike Lee asked her to debut in Do the Right Thing, a movie in which Ruth brought out the African Pop Culture — vibrant crop top, necklaces, shorts. She loved to research the colors of times, the economics of the time, how people lived in those times, everything about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruth’s dynamism to understand people was instilled by her mother. Her mother taught her to empathize with people which later helped her to understand people deeply. Ruth observes the style of people walking down the street and interprets their culture, their beginning, what they care about. 
In 2019, Ruth got the opportunity to create the world of Black Panther. It was an immense task to explore the reigns of ancient indigenous tribes around Africa which are vast resources of Artistic ideas. She infused the cultural and African diaspora with the realm of fantasy and futuristic world of Black Panther. Introduction of Killmonger in western contemporary dress to Dora Milaje’s ethnic colors of Africa depicted ethnic groups of Wakanda and defined colonialism. She was awarded an Oscar for her artistic and well-defined designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her work has always left people awestruck. She brings humanity, emotionality to life through her clothes in a way that they are not only historically accurate but that can imagine black lives that the history books have told us wasn’t possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Ruth-Carter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Ruth-Carter/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 029, Enneagrams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We start small and innocent in this world. Life was safe inside the womb. But as soon as we are born, we struggle to breathe. It is an indication that life is sometimes painful. No one likes pain and it is human nature to protect ourselves from the pain. To cope with these fears we cast an armour around us which gradually moulds our personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are born with the fear of falling and loud sounds. As we grow old and face the unusual problems we get afraid and thereby develop a defense mechanism. Seldom do we lose ourselves and start to think that our personality armour is who we truly are which causes all kinds of problems in life. Wouldn’t it be great if we understand ourselves and identify personality armour? One of the tools that help us in modeling this is Enneagram. It illustrates the nine archetypal human character structures. It is an ancient symbol of thoughts with a psychological origin.  Scientists consider it as skeptical because of its muddled history. But it is a great tool for fiction writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enneagram describes nine core types of human personality based on the dominant fear. Of course, there are more fears and we will experience most of them at some points in our life. But deep down there is a dominant fear that controls us. This fundamental fear changes our life and we look at the world through the lens of the armour of this fear. This lens might distort our view and more importantly, everyone has a different lens. If we can understand the world view of other people, it would help us get along with people better. We could have better relationships, better families and better lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Enneagram system, following are the 9 fundamental fears:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of Being Evil :&lt;/strong&gt; This is the fear of being bad, corrupt or evil. People with this fear strive to be correct and good, feeling that if they don’t meet this expectation they are unworthy. 
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Reformer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being unloved :&lt;/strong&gt; These characters want people to love them. In order to achieve it, they care for other people and start to love them expecting others to love them back. These generous and empathetic people are often disappointed by what they get in return.
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Helper&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being Worthless :&lt;/strong&gt; People who have this fear want to be valuable and worthwhile. They crave attention and are eager to impress. They fear failure and humiliation.
 This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Achiever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being Insignificant :&lt;/strong&gt; or the fear of being without identity, people who feel so are trying to figure out their true identity. They are their true original self, and use creative means to express their inner feelings.
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Artist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being incompetent :&lt;/strong&gt; These characters have curiosity and a deep desire for knowledge and understanding some skill. 
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Investigator&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being without support :&lt;/strong&gt; People with this fear crave for constant guidance and security. They are hardworking, committed and good at foreseeing risks.
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Loyalist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being deprived :&lt;/strong&gt; People who feel this fear are charismatic and enthusiastic. They have a great appetite for life and aim for more experience. 
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Adventurer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of being controlled :&lt;/strong&gt; They want to control their environment and be in their own control. They are great leaders, highly independent and self-confident.
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Leader&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of separation :&lt;/strong&gt; They are optimistic people who hate conflict around them. They see the best in others and in the world. 
This is character type of &lt;em&gt;The Peacemaker&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of Course we possess some traits of each of these fears but one fear dominates and shapes our personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. Enneagrams are generally used to model the characters of the protagonist in fiction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Enneagram/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Enneagram/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 028, Honey Bees</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Honey Bees are the most collaborative species in the world. Each hive comprises thousands of bees working together in order to build and sustain the colony. Within the colony, each bee is assigned with a role. Queen’s job is simple — she creates the foundation of the beehive and lay eggs for future generations. There is usually a single queen in the hive. Also, queen bees have the duty to regulate the hive’s activities. Worker bees are female bees who take care of housekeeping of the hive, foraging, feeding the queen bee and drones, taking care of larvae, and collecting pollen and nectar. They work so hard that their life span is around 6 weeks. And lastly, the drones are male bees whose main role is to mate. They are most active during spring and summer and die as winter approaches. Fun fact is that male bee can mate only once and dies soon after it. This is because the ejaculation is so strong that it ruptures endophallus, leaving the bulb of endophallus inside the queen bee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a brain the size of a seed, how do bees have such great work ethics? It is part of their genes and it starts with the queen bee who has the unique ability to designate the sex of her children. Besides this, bees are excellent mathematicians, they can calculate angles and also comprehend the roundness of the earth. But the most important mathematical marvel in honey bees’ life is their hive. The design of the hive is perfect. Bees need a safe place to secure their entire colony and a place to store nectar which will ripe into honey. For this, they need some serious space optimization. They use honey wax to make the hive. But the problem is that a single ounce of honey wax is produced from eight ounces of honey. In order to minimize their work and design a safe and spacious hive, they develop Hexagonal structure — this uses the least amount of honey wax, provides the most amount of space and  also provides a sturdier structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The honeycomb structure isn’t the only contribution of Honey Bees. They produce honey, a sugary syrup with medicinal property. Bees eat insects that damage crop like mites, spiders and also help in pollination. Moreso, One out of three meals eaten by humans is made possible because of honey bees. They help winemakers by biting grapes and kickstarting fermentation. If all honey bees die, the plant will slowly start to deteriorate leading to starvation of millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey bees are disappearing at a very rapid rate. Disease, parasite or starvation doesn’t conclude to this cause, there is more to it. This mysterious disappearance of bees is known as Colony Collapse Disorder. Despite the fact that scientists do not surely know the exact reason, they have suggested : Pesticides and chemicals, depriving queen bees’ immunity due to hybridization of bees to produce honey on commercial levels, stress because of human activities and many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey bees are now fighting for survival. It would be a catastrophe if they lost this fight. This is a conundrum we have to solve if we want to continue to live with an abundance and diversity of food. We are deeply connected to other life forms and we have to take better care of our surroundings — if not for the beauty of nature but at least for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Honey-Bees/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Honey-Bees/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 027, Onion Peel Experiment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Woohoo! Finally, we were going to visit the Biology Lab. Class 9 was an innocuous period — Little did we know, little did we bother. Just like any other day, I dressed up and cycled my way to school. Bell rang and It was our biology class and the teacher entered the class. Professor Afsar Khan had a weird personality — witty and strict at the same time. We never understood if we should laugh at his jokes or not. If we did he might scold us and if we didn’t we might disrespect his joke. Despite this, he was a brilliant teacher. But an unusual thing happened as he entered the class, while we were taking out our notebooks he asked us to pack our bags. At first, we were confused because he has never asked us to do so but later we thought he would take us to the ground and we will play. Instead, we were going to perform an experiment — Onion Peel Experiment — in the Biology Lab. And, for those of you who don’t know, it was our first time in any kind of laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The silence of our class broke out and it seemed like a fish market — everyone was super excited, but our teacher had a dead look on his face. In a matter of seconds, we formed a queue, which otherwise used to take an eternity, and jollily marched through the corridor. And as a matter of fact, for students of boys school, we behaved the best. No one jumped the queue, none stopped for toilet or water break, and even the disinterested students were gleaming. As we approached the laboratory, our Lab Assistant unlocked the lab. As soon as we had a glimpse of the lab, our jaws dropped. We did not expect anything like that in our old school building but little did we know, we never saw a lab before. It seemed like Potions class from Harry Potter, there were jars of different specimens all around us. Skeleton hung by the wall, there were diagrams of plant and animal reproductive parts. Boys started to conspire about all of them and came up with the most unlikely theories and ambitions. However silly they seem now, they all made sense in 9th standard. I vividly remember one, a friend of mine claimed, on seeing a brain inside a jar, that the brain belonged to Albert Einstein which left us all in awe. While we were extending our eyes as far as we could, Professor Afsar grabbed our attention and started to explain the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asked us to take a piece of chopped onion and told us that the lab assistant will provide tools. Professor Afsar asked us to start performing the experiment but everyone was blankly staring at each other because we were so deeply engulfed that anyone barely cared to listen. There was awkwardness in the environment and our teachers could sense it and they loved to feed on it, so did Professor Afsar. He gave us a piece of his mind, but he explained it to us again. We were asked to take off onion peel, place it on watch glass, then add safranin and let it soak. Then wash the peel with water, soak it in extra water, add a drop of glycerine and then examine it under the microscope to observe the plant cell. It might seem simple now, but we found an opportunity to mischief at each step. Aware of the danger that Professor is watching, we fought for a bigger onion piece with a tweezer as our sword and watch glass as our shield. In another corner of the laboratory, students were pinching each other with a tweezer, some of the students tried to create music by clicking tweezers together. The impressive thing was that Professor Afsar did not lose his cool, it seemed like he had already experienced all of this earlier as well. Once in a while, he took a check on us and taunted us for not doing any work. As the class was about to get over, he created two watch glasses and put it under two microscopes because we all were too busy with our own stupidity. He asked us to form two queues and look at the onion peel through the microscope. No one understood what they were looking at and what was the purpose of it. Everyone was having the time of their life while some students were still in line and the bell rang. Students in the queue looked disappointed but Professor Afsar allowed them to fulfill their wishes to look into nothingness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We packed our bags and walked back to classes as if we had just performed a surgery. This was the most fulfilling day of our school life.
And Period.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Onion-Peel-Experiment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Onion-Peel-Experiment/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 026, Over-the-top (OTT) media services</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The innovation of moving frames was invented by Lumière Brothers and today we are in the age of Netflix, Disney+, Hotstar etc. The technology of cinema has evolved. Things changed from the black and white moving images to hours of UltraHD video footage with binaural noise to movies that have a whole lot of visual effects to movies made of computer-generated images. In terms of technology, first came the television age, then a lot of private channels which brought in a lot more entertainment, then came the era of CDs and DVDs and finally the advent of broadband gave way to Over-the-top media services and now we can stream the movie that we want, the show that we want, the documentary that we want anytime, anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The streaming revolution is here — the next great leap in how the world gets its entertainment is here.  With thousands of hours of content on OTT platforms, this age can be termed as the golden age of OTT. OTTs are doing more than evolving the TV format; OTT is growing, both for consumers and advertisers. For consumers, the accessibility of the content on multiple screens anytime and anywhere makes it more engaging. And advertisers can show personalized advertisements. Also, OTT platforms often help in the production of numerous movies, shows and documentaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the boom in network technologies and internet speed, people have started to consume more content. Customers are slowly cutting off their cable connection and switching to OTT platforms. OTTs provide the consumer to view specified content despite Television. The subscription-based media consumption provides an abundance of particular media streams through one channel while television provides a plethora of channels to view but a limited number of options of a particular genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OTTs are evolving as well. With every new feature they add to their platform, other platforms try to incorporate it to make more monetary benefits. In the fiscal year 2019, OTT platforms in India had a market value of ₹3500 crores and slowly the market is expanding. We don’t know what the future of streaming looks like but we surely know it will provide a diversity of streams on a given platform.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/OTTs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/OTTs/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 025, N-Queen Problem </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Chess is a game of multi facets and has lots of mysteries with each piece. One piece, in particular, assumed to be most powerful right after the king, the queen has made up a puzzle, the N-queens problem —  try to place N queens on a N\(\times\)N chessboard so that none of the queens attacks each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially devised for the 8\(\times\)8 chess, that is to place queens such that none attack each other. The problem to find all the solutions to the 8-Queen problem is computationally expensive as there are &lt;sub&gt;64&lt;/sub&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; (= 4,42,61,65,368) possibilities out of which there are only 92 solutions. Is there a solution better than brute force? Given the constraints of Queens’ move, we can narrow down the possibilities. If we consider the straight movement of the queen we can narrow down the number to 8&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; (= 1,67,77,216) which can be further punched down to 8! =(40,320) by permuting the diagonal move of the queen. Out of the 92 solutions mentioned, if we do not consider symmetry operation of reflection and rotation then we are left with only 12 solutions. But as N goes up, the value of N! goes up and causes trouble of computability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this time complexity can be optimized by using backtracking algorithms. Backtracking is a recursive process where the queen is placed on the edge and ideally saves the possible attacks. Then another queen is placed at a safe position and the process is repeated. However, if the N queens cannot be placed at safe positions then the algorithm backtracks and then try another safe position. This takes around 2&lt;sup&gt;N&lt;/sup&gt; steps in the worst case which is 100 times faster than the brute-force algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can still speed up the algorithm on the cost of storage. Known as Branch and Bound, this algorithm is similar to backtracking (described in the previous paragraph) but keeps a track of the state of the board to prevent any unnecessary recursion. There are numerous other algorithms, some more efficient, others less but none of the algorithms has helped to cross the barrier to place 26 safe queens on 26\(\times\)26 chessboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreso, as the size of the board increases, the number of solutions to place the queens increases exponentially. Funnily,  for 5\(\times\)5 boards there are 10 distinct solutions and for 6\(\times\)6 boards the number of solutions drops to 4. There is no formula to calculate the number of solutions nor can we figure out the asymptotic limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the N-queen problem, several other puzzles emerge from chessboard like knights’ tours. I sometimes wonder if we can ever explore all the possible states of a chessboard and come up with new puzzles, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Queen-Problem/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Queen-Problem/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 024, Mechanical Keyboard</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Keychron, Corsair, Razer — THOCK! soothing, satisfying, clickety-clack sounds, we are talking about Mechanical Keyboards. Mechanical Keyboards have become popular in the last decade. You might ask that the ₹500 one does the same thing. This is absolutely true; we can’t deny that the cheap one does the same as the mechanical keyboard. Then why should you invest your money to buy these expensive, custom mechanical keyboards? Because keyboards are essentials we use in everyday life, so like other day-to-day items, why not get something that may potentially better your experience? But what other options do we have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Membrane keyboards, the cheaper keyboards have a layer of silicon rubber matrix between the keys and the PCB. Each key is held with a rubber dome and gets activated only when the key is pressed all the way down to PCB. It is more like hitting your fingers on a hard surface — in the long run, it’s bad for fingers until you want your hands to look like Dr. Strange. But, in mechanical keyboards keys get activated on reaching the actuation point which means you don’t have to push all the way down. The cool thing about mechanical keyboards is their variety and the ability to choose a keyboard which meets your requirements. Variety as in, how the keypress feels, layout, programmability, aesthetics, materials and so on which is very limited to membrane keyboards. Do not want a number pad? Get rid of it; Need dedicated macros? Create them; Want better ergonomics? Get a split or ergonomic keyboard; Do you like the retro look? Just find a retro-looking keyboard or keycaps. It’s all out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just because of mechanical keyboards, instead because of the mechanical switches, which helps in modularity and customisation. This isn’t something you can control with membrane keyboards because they are just a sheet of collapsing domes. But with mechanical keyboards, you can get a range of switches — clicky, tactile, or smooth linear switches, loud, silent whatever you want. Getting something you use in daily life, that feels good, can improve your performance, efficiency and add enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the functional side. The durability of key switches is around 50 million keystrokes which mean mechanical keyboards go for ages. Adding to it, mechanical keyboards are sturdier, heavier and nicely built. The orchestra of CHOK CHOK and CLICK CLICK has added symphony to our gaming, typing and programming experience. Mechanical keyboards are true works of art.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Mechanical-Keyboards/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Day 023, Bright side of quarantine in students life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished two assignments! Oh really? Ok Ok, I copied. This was the closest I can get to college now. I am graduating in 2020, Will I? Who knows? We are the batch of 2020 (if so). While everyone else was ranting about colleges and assignments, I was telling them it’s for their own good. Now it came on me and I feel it’s my responsibility to say a word or two. Is it? No. We are already hammered by the negativity floating on the internet. Instead, we should go somewhere silly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zooms calls have given us the opportunity to attend classes on Pluto, Sun, Golden Gate Bridge, even inside the Pacific Ocean with fishes but my friends chose to study under hanging underwear. Aha! This is how to attain enlightenment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alright, we ain’t getting a graduation party but you can always get high on sanitizer, higher than The Empire States building. JK!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students of engineering college, also known as hunter-gatherers have successfully proved this title wrong. Thanks to home! The control we got on our tongue, otherwise cursing every now and then; the dreams of getting 8 hrs of sleep are now being accomplished daily with the compensation of sleep we missed during Fifa and Sheesha, and all the healthy food instead of rubber butter at college canteen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Although it’s established that I cannot cook but we can cook almost every cuisine at home — we will save money and time. Moreso who found this hobby, please don’t give this up. And to all the restaurants and hotels and college mess, no no not college mess — Fuck You — for forking out money from the pool of our tiny pockets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In other news, the attendance criterion is lifted. We can sleep extra, we can binge-watch the shows and not get overwhelmed by the class the next day, because there are none. But, Netflix and zizz — the most adorable things are becoming boring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To all those people whose birthdays are spent in quarantine, Happy Birthday and Congratulations! You have saved yourself from the brutal birthday bumps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this pandemic is a test of your immunity — immunity to bullshit, immunity to hatred, immunity to selfishness, immunity to indulgence and yes, to a virus. Just hang in there people, 2020 is a rollercoaster ride. We will get through this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Qurantine-College/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
